<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The church triumphant, or, A comfortable treatise of the amplitude and largeness of the kingdom of Christ wherein is proved by Scriptures and reason, that the number of the damned is inferiour to that of the elect / by Joseph Alford ...</title>
            <author>Alford, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26659</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12488324</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12488324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26659)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 302:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The church triumphant, or, A comfortable treatise of the amplitude and largeness of the kingdom of Christ wherein is proved by Scriptures and reason, that the number of the damned is inferiour to that of the elect / by Joseph Alford ...</title>
                  <author>Alford, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Bentley for J. Williams at the Crown in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kingdom of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHURCH Triumphant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A Comfortable Treatiſe, of the Amplitude and Large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Kingdom of <hi>CHRIST;</hi> Wherein is proved, by Scriptures and Reaſon, <hi>That the number of the</hi> Damned <hi>is inferiour to that of the</hi> Elect.</p>
            <q>Nè Redarguas ea falſitatis de quorum contrariis non eſt demonſtratio. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rabbi Moſ.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOSEPH ALFORD, <hi>M. A.</hi> ſometime of <hi>Oriell</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Exercere nos Deus vult diffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ultate Quaeſtionis,</l>
               <l>Non decipere falſitate ſententiae. <bibl>
                     <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>W. Bentley,</hi> for <hi>J. William<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at the Crown in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1649.</p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62319:2"/>
            <p>with that uſefull obſervation of <hi>Irenaeus:</hi> who ſpeaking of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies,</hi> and ſome other abſtruſe points in Religion ſaith, <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam effectum habent aenigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt, &amp; ambiguitates homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus;</hi> they are clouds in the eyes, and riddles in the underſtandings of men, until they be explained. I humbly intreat you therefore to accept my indeavours, and to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend your judgement till you have weighed the Reaſons on both ſides. Let not the ſeeming novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the opinion retard your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, for although Truth be the daughter of the moſt High, and therefore there can be no new Truth: yet many Errours are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, embraced, reverenced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifted and uncontroverted, meerly in regard of their Antiquity: when
<pb facs="tcp:62319:2"/> notwithſtanding ſome doctrines of great conſolation may languiſh and be ſuppreſſed under thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. The treaſures of Divine knowledge are inexhauſtible, and to the diſſolution of the World, the Oracles of God will ſuppeditate new matter, wherewith to recreate a holy diligence, to confirm a doubting ſpirit, and to confound a ſawcy curioſity. If I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a truth unto the world, which hath lien as an Embrion buried in the womb of errour, it is a wealthy bleſsing upon my poor endeavours. If I doe hallucinate in the proſecution of it, I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be confuted without obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy. I am not leſs deſirous to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh an errour, than I am ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous to hearken to a corrected judgement. Sir, I wiſh you feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities
<pb facs="tcp:62319:3"/> both temporal and eternal, that when you have finiſhed the progreſs of faith and hope, you may be tranſlated into this <hi>Church Triumphant</hi> together, <hi>Sir,</hi> with</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt devoted ſervant JOS. ALFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62319:3"/>
            <head>OF THE LARGENESSE OF THE <hi>Church Triumphant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Miſteries of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſome queſtions are not yet un-muffled from their obſcurity: This Doctrine concerning the Paucity or Multitude of the Elect, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of conſolation, and conducible to the knowledge of God, hath ſeemed not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difficult, but inexplicable. The opinion of the Learned aſſerting the Paucity, hath augmented the Difficulty, as if the bare au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of men were ſufficient to prevail with after Ages without the concurrence of their reaſons. It hath been inveloped with obſcurity, by a ſurmize, that the knowledge of it is hid in the ſecret councel of God, and is to us unrevealed: neither hath it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62319:4"/> appeared what reaſons can be raiſed from the Doctrine of Faith and good Works, which might greatly perſwade us to a belief of the greater number to be ſaved. But the clouds of erroneous prejudice being diſſipated, truth will be man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſted in a more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous excellency.</p>
            <p>What tidings can arrive more acceptable to a conſternated ſpirit, labouring under ſin and an apprehenſion of eternal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than to receive an aſſurance, that between the exhauſtible mercy of his God, and his iniquities, there is no proportion. That the goodneſs of God is not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the ſalvation of ſome few men, juſt, and perfect, and eminent for ſanctity; but that he will beautifie innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, lame, and infirm, and diſlocated mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: On the other ſide, what can more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the hearts of men to deſperation, than to feign God to be ſome ſevere and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Exactor, who will admit none into his Heavenly Kingdom, but <hi>Enoch, Elias,</hi> Prophets, and Apoſtles, and ſome few men of Angelical holineſs. For as in the body all the members are not Eyes, but the Ears, the Noſe, the Hands, the Feet, and other more ignoble parts, have their diſtinct and proper functions: So in the Body of the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> whereof our Lord Chriſt is the Head, the members are divers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62319:4"/> and ſubordinate, ſome being dignified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others: and as in a well conſtituted City, there are the chief Magiſtrates, men of middle ranks, and the poorer ſort: ſo in the City of God, which through his benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is congregated, and conſtituted by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in this world, there will be found not onely Prophets and Apoſtles, but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inferior perſons out of all Kingdoms, People, and Nations. In the Tabernacle of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and upon the building and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of that illuſtrious Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> they did not onely beſtow gold, ſilver, and jewels, but they made uſe alſo of braſs, wood, ſtones, Badgers-ſkins, and Goat-ſkins: to let us underſtand no doubt, that into this Heavenly Temple, whereof that was a ſhadow, ſome ſhall be received, who in the judgement of men, want the auſtere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and refined piety. But if any man object, Nothing that is defiled and impure ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, and that God hath commanded us to be holy, even as He is holy: Let that man alſo know, that he, who upon the Croſs purified the thief, in the fire of his own ſacrifice and torments, will in like manner deal with all thoſe that are ordained to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. It is the commandement of God that we ſhould be perfect, but imperfect is that charity that refuſeth ſalvation to thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62319:5"/> that have not fulfilled that commandment he commandeth what we are unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, that the riches of his mercy might abound, to make the whole world obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his benignity: for by the fulfilling of the law, or the accumulation of good works, no man can be perfectly juſt before him.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe I have framed this Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Amplitude of the Kingdom of God, conceiving it no leſs profitable than if it had conſiſted of the Mercy, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wiſdom, Power, or in a word, of the Nature of God. For theſe things are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenated, knit, and interwoven, that unleſs the confines of it exceed the territories of the devil, we can neither truly apprehend his mercy, nor thoſe other attributes that declare his nature.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the peeviſhneſs of ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, they chooſe rather to defend an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with obſtinacy which they dote upon, than to enquire what may be ſtedfaſtly maintained without contumacy; but we who defend the better Cauſe, to wit, the magnifying of the Mercy of God in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Mankind (for beyond theſe we ſhall not proceed) are prepared to refute without pertinacity, and to be convinced without paſſion.</p>
            <p>I have not enterpriſed this Diſputation with any ſecret end divided from the glory
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62319:5"/> of God, not to anticipate more able pens, nor to introduce any ſuperannuated Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; not to tyrannize over the judgements of men by an upſtart Opinion, nor to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a neceſſity of belief upon the meaneſt capacity: but to unboſom my Meditations to the Pious and the Learned, and to have this liberty judged by the Church of Chriſt according to the Divine Oracles of Truth; for in this caſe I wiſh not to hear the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this or that man, but, if it could be accompliſhed, of all men. If in the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Scriptures, mine ſeem diſcrepant from the underſtanding of another man, let him not raſhly reject it, but remember that all Chriſtian Commonwealths have indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this priviledeg to a Writer, to produce his own perſwaſion without the contumely of anothers judgement. For why ſhould that liberty be prejudged by him, who is at liberty to exerciſe it? Let them conſider whether any thing be alleadged againſt the Analogy of Faith, or the precepts of good Life: any thing inconſiſtent with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt undoubted principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, or derogatory from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and glory of the Kingdom of Chriſt, of Allegories and miſtical Interpretations. I ſhall ſpeak little, knowing with what free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom all Writers have made uſe of them, provided they have not been repugnant to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62319:6"/> the Doctrine of Chriſt. It was my deſire to attempt whether this Argument might not be publiſhed as a Paradox, and after the cuſtom of the ancient Schools diſcuſſed on both ſides, that ſo from the ſucceſs of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, there might out of things obſcure and wonderful, flow matter probable and common.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſaid in the beginning, that ſome things in the ſecrets of Divinity are not yet explained, this perhaps will not eſcape reprehenſion: for it may be reinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, That not onely all things neceſſary to ſalvation are contained in the Scriptures, but that all thoſe things are unfolded and made plain both by ancient and modern Writers: and therefore it appears a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thing to enquire after new lights.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, that nothing more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably ought to be believed, than that God by the pens of his Prophets, Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and Prophets, hath delivered unto us in their writings, whatſoever it was his good pleaſure we ſhould know, and obſerve: but I ſay alſo I have (I believe) reaſon to pawſe upon the conſequence, that becauſe there they are contained, they are therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, for this I ſuppoſe no judgement that is at leaſure can believe; for if there be a perfect Declaration of all thoſe things, wherefore are our precious hours puniſhed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62319:6"/> with ſo many Commentaries? why are ſo many books written to work down, ſmooth, and explicate the knotty queſtions in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? why ſo many diſputations, conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and controverſies among the learned? for whileſt they emit Explications, Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, Annotations, and Animadverſions, do they not diſcipline reaſon to preponder ſome things as yet intricate and perplexed? and inſtruct a conſideration that they labour to propagate belief to things doubtful, and authority to things contemned? if any man will be ſo licentious as to reply, that ſuch polemical diſceptations are ſpent for the moſt part about matters of indifferency, beſides the untruth of it, certainly learned and wiſe men have reaſon to reſent it as a horrible indignity to hear themſelves char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to waſt their time in unneceſſary alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
            <p>But what age may not make the ſame ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that all things are abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed? Antiquity might plead it, and then it had been a needleſs undertaking to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and declare the meaning of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Future generations alſo that ſhall ſucceed us even to the worlds diſſolution, may affirm the ſame thing, ſo that by ſuch a reſtraint all means of interpreting the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical places of Scripture, would be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more precluded. That the ſenſe of divers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62319:7"/> places of Scripture, hath not been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declared in any age, is ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> where he hath ordained propheſie to continue in the Church for ever: by this means to inform our underſtandings, that the enucleation of ſome abſtruſe matters hath the preheminence amongſt Spiritual gifts. In his firſt Epiſtle alſo to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> he gives it in precept, That we quench not the Spirit, neither deſpiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyings, but exhorteth us to examine all things, and to hold faſt that which is good. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo doth not deny, but that ſome things in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> are hard to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>Thus it is evident, I wanted not reaſon to affirm, that ſome queſtions in the Sacred Monuments of Chriſtian Religion, are ſtill complicated and involved: neither is the Spring-head of this holy Fountain ſo to be ſhut or dammed up, that it may not be lawful for any to convey the ſtreams to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Celeſtial <hi>Eden</hi> the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps may fancy that this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion might have been ſtifled in the birth, or overlaid by ſecond thoughts, becauſe it ſeems to graduate men in diſſoluteneſs; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them from an awful reverence into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, from ſecurity to contempt, and from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62319:7"/> contempt, to an unreſtrained courſe of life. Errours proceeding from a good intention are the more excuſable; and that they doe e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re through a miſunderſtanding of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of piety, I ſhall now demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>Fear never made good Tutour to duty, but love and a conſideration of benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. 'Tis the method of ſlavery to act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der compulſion; but it is the glorie of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience when affection extorteth a filial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Thus when Moſes in the ſixth of <hi>Deuter.</hi> had ſet down all the laws, ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous as is were of our obſerving them, he brings in the law of Charitie, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to love God above all things, and our neighbour as our ſelves. Our Lord Chriſt alſo brought no other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment but this of Love, making it the epitome of the Law and the Prophets. From hence S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo in the 13 to the <hi>Rom.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Love is the fulfilling of the Law.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> alſo that boſom-friend of his Lord and Maſter, when he would deſcribe unto us the perfection of it, by the nature of God, telleth us, <hi>God is Love,</hi> inſinuating that <hi>he that abideth in Love abideth in God, and God in him.</hi> Seing therefore the Law, the Prophets, the Lord, and his Apoſtles, do unanimouſly invite to love; conſidering al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that love floweth not from fear (for fear and love are never conſociated, love ſtill
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62319:8"/> expelling fear) but from the love of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other towards us, which alſo is known by indulgence and conferring of favours and benefits: it follows that the eſſence of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſanctity is rooted in the aſſurance of the Divine love to us, and quickened by the conſideration, and eſtimation of Gods great benefits unto us: which apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions enflame our ſouls to reaflect and obey him.</p>
            <p>That our Lord Chriſt held this to be the path of true piety the Scriptures doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and therefore David ſaith unto the Lord, <hi>righteouſneſs thou haſt loved, but wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dneſs thou haſt hated.</hi> For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more virtuous and effectual to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the mind to an exaltation of piety, and to keep it at that pitch, than Love, and a continual remembrance of the Divine clemency and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>But this is undiſcernable in the ſalvation of a few men, and the condemnation of many. In this rather was the mercy of God manifeſted, that when in Juſtice he might have damned all, hee deſtinated ſome to puniſhment, but more to ſalvation: for when the ſoul ſpringeth, and culminateth in the contemplation of ſuch a love, unleſs it be doomed to the left-hand diſtribution, that man muſt needs abhor vice, when he knoweth it is ſo diſpleaſing to ſo loving a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62319:8"/> father. And it will alſo forcibly allure him to the love of virtue, and piety, becauſe he remembreth the indulgence of his God, doth require it of, and expect it from him. Laſtly he will continually endeavour to be holy, innocent, and juſt, becauſe he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his God, and his Saviour is holy, pure, innocent, and juſt. Nor doth the objected ſecurity hinder at all the jou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ney of piety, but may rather be accounted the life of good actions, and a happy being: but ſuch a condition of life cannot poſſibly be eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to a perpetual fear of evil, and torment. Neither doe I underſtand and mean by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that carnal habit, which ariſeth from a contempt of Gods laws, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy of the day of judgement: but a privation of anxiety, and a tranquillity of ſpirit, germinating and budding from a confidence of the Divine goodneſs to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, which our Lord and his Apoſtles have called Peace.</p>
            <p>In this ſecurity and affiance, I ſay, felicity is placed, and I term it the fountain of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and good works. What good things can he imagine, what laudable action can he meditate, or what great matters worthy of a Chriſtian reſolution can he perform, that alwayes doubts his own ſalvation? that thinketh God is angry with the greater part of mankind? and entertaineth ſuch narrow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62319:9"/> conceptions of the kingdom of Chriſt, as if it were open but to ſome few men, I know not who in ſome angle and nook of the World? This is not to extol his Majeſty, but to obſcure it; this is not to advance his glorie, but to diminiſh it; not to magnifie his goodneſs, but to diſparage it; not to admire his wiſdom, but to deſpiſe it; not to ſtand amazed at his omnipotence, but to mock it: whereas they who think highly and Honourably (as it is meet they ſhould) of the <hi>Largeneſs of his Kingdom,</hi> their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations are devout, pious, and the more congruous to the eſſence of God. Of which moſt bleſſed kingdom what my concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, I ſhall comprehend in two books, or Dialogues; in the laſt I ſhall variouſly, and plainly demonſtrate the largeneſs of this Kingdom, having in the firſt cleared all thoſe places of Scripture which ſeem to oppoſe the magnitude of it.</p>
            <p>For diſtinction ſake I name the Prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours <hi>Caelius,</hi> and <hi>Maynardus,</hi> and every at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Reader may make himſelf a Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caelius.</speaker>
               <p>I come accompanied (my dear <hi>Maynardus</hi>) with early deſires to renew our laſt conference; and if it be no interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your ſtudies, I ſhould deſire ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in a ſcruple, by ſome words of yours injected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62319:9"/>
               <speaker>Maynardus.</speaker>
               <p>I account it (my <hi>Caelius</hi>) the nobleſt end of my ſtudies, if by that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage I can in any matter benefit a friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You may remember, that after you had diſcourſed of the goodneſs and mercy of God to mankind in Chriſt, you added that his kingdom, which was built upon, and eſtabliſhed in mercy, was ſet open to more men, than many men have hitherto conjectured. I have ruminated upon theſe words, being doubtfull whither they might tend: and many things coming to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberance I remain unreſolved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Speak, I pray, your thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt I thought of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igen,</hi> who (as it is ſaid) was of Opinion that not onely the damned Souls of men, but alſo the Devils themſelves at laſt ſhould be received unto mercy. I thought alſo upon their opinion who believed, that although not all men, yet ſuch as were matriculated into Chriſt by Baptiſm, and did eat of his myſtical bread, ſhould obtain eternal life. Laſtly I pondered whether you might not inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate that the number of the Elect was not inferiour to that of the Damned, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greater.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And which of theſe did you find moſt agreeable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The laſt, but that the Scriptures teach us otherwiſe, ſeems the more probable. But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62319:10"/> becauſe nothing falleth unadviſedly from you, I expect the reaſon of your words: and whether you intended them in any of theſe ſenſes which I have delivered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt I conceive that opinion to be falſly impoſed upon <hi>Orig n,</hi> and that it is an emulous invention of ſuch men that would obſcure his eminence, which unworthy practice thoſe times (ſo well as theſe) were very prone too. For my part, I conceive that moſt learned man to have advanced the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the mercy of God, by no reproveable or vulgar amplifications, which ſaying being maliciouſly detorted through envy, and perverſly underſtood by ignorance, that devout Father was ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to affirm that the devil ſhould be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to glorious immortality: But this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, whether held by <hi>Origen</hi> or any other man, is ſufficiently refuted by Chriſt himſelf the Maſter of Truth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond opinion, which doth inveſt all thoſe with eternal happineſs, which are initiated by Baptiſm into, and have partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated the Body and Blood of Chriſt, is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to be rejected and diſ-allowed; for that imputeth ſalvation to the efficacy of outward ſigns and elements: but this is ſo ſuper-abundantly overthrown by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that it were waſte of time to urge any thing in confutation of it: for it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62319:10"/> by unavoidable conſequence, if that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſhould be granted, that <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> of whom <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention; that <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> nay that <hi>Sergius</hi> the Monk, who by ſome hath been reputed Antichriſt, are now par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Beatitude.</p>
               <p>But the third opinion, that the City of God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> ſhould be larger than the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable ſynagogue of the devil, doth not ſeem to my judgement to contain the leaſt abſurdity. Wherefore I ſhall not conceal my preconceptions of it, unleſs you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conceive of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould (as I ſaid before) embrace this perſwaſion, did not the word of God reſtrain my conſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Doth neither the authority of the ancient Fathers, nor the conſent of former ages, nor the newneſs and greatneſs of a matter then prevail with you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not at all. For firſt, in diſputation, not the authority of men, but the power of reaſon ſhould be of moſt importance. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the Fathers claim not the leaſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their writings, further than they are confirmed by the teſtimonies of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Then, for the conſent of many ages and cuſtoms, what is it, if it be not ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62319:11"/> by reaſon, and the authentical authority of Gods word, but a decrepit and a blind errour? For there is no novelty in Truth, than which nothing is more ancient, for ſhe is the Daughter of the Moſt High. But if there be a truth newly explorated, the greatneſs and the newneſs of it, ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allure, than affright me, or any other man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You would then, did not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures over-rule you, joyn your conſent to this Opinion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I would.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Verily I applaud your judgement, as holy, and worthy of a Chriſtian. But what places are thoſe which (as you ſay) contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict this Opinion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The firſt is, becauſe at the Deluge onely eight perſons were ſaved, and if the ſalvation of the Elect were typified by this deliverance, doubtleſs the number of the Elect is very ſmall: but this ſeems confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by S. <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. where ſpeaking of the Ark, he ſaith, <hi>In which very few, that is eight Souls were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</hi> The like Figure whereunto even Baptiſm doth now alſo ſave us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe words of S. <hi>Peter</hi> rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, do unfold the myſtery of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Firſt he ſaith, that the waters of the floud, were ſhadows or figures of Baptiſm,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62319:11"/> and the deſtruction of ſin; therefore <hi>Noah</hi> did typifie Chriſt the Publiſher and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Righteouſneſs, and by the Ark is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the faith of the Kingdom of Chriſt: for as none were preſerved from the waters, but thoſe who hearkening to <hi>Noah,</hi> took ſanctuary in the Ark; ſo now alſo none en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the door of Salvation, but ſuch as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard the Goſpel preached, believing, repent: and following Chriſt Jeſus the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot of his Heavenly Ark the Church, are waſted by faith as in a ſhip through the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging waves and whirlpits of death and hell. Whereas <hi>Peter</hi> ſubjoyns that very few were ſaved from the deluge, thoſe words may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aptly be referred to the paucity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews</hi> at his firſt manifeſtation in the fleſh. For <hi>James</hi> alſo writing to the <hi>Jews</hi> ſcattered about all the coaſts of <hi>Aſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth them, that they be not dejected through various tribulations, nor diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged through the paucity of believers: and ſheweth them alſo that the ſufferings of Chriſt, the perſecutions of the Godly, and the ſcarcity of thoſe Jews that ſhould free themſelves from that hallucination, and blindneſs of mind, was foretold by the Prophets, and prefigured by types: and as that inundation deſtroyed not them that took ſhelter in the Ark, neither can croſſes, calamities, nor death it ſelf endamage thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62319:12"/> that truſt in Chriſt, but be rather wholly converted to the advantage of a believing ſoul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> therefore, as I have ſhewed, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of the univerſality of the Elect, but his words muſt be reſtrained to thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Jews, to whom, as he was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the Circumciſion, he directed that Epiſtle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs with joy my <hi>Maynardus,</hi> thou haſt enlightned a very dark paſſage in S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> but what can you anſwer to this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that of that vaſt multitude of Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites which God brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> onely two, <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> and <hi>Joſuah,</hi> were admitted into the Land of Promiſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The beſt and ſafeſt rule to unvail the myſteries of the Old Teſtament, is to conſult the Apoſtolical ſenſe of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Paul</hi> handling that place in the tenth chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> draweth it into example, thereby to warn and deter them from ſinning by the ſad preſident of thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that fell in the Wilderneſs: And in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that he may diſcover the root of all iniquity, he ſaith that they to whom the Land of the Canaanites was promiſed, and they who fled out of <hi>Egypt</hi> through unbelief ſhould not poſſeſs that land, which God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there called his Reſt, becauſe it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62319:12"/> the peace and unity of the Kingdom and Church of Chriſt, in which we ſhall live ſecure, truſting in the good will of God towards us in Jeſus Chriſt. Of which reſt the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> maketh mention in the two and thirtieth chapter, ſaying: <hi>And my people ſhall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in ſure dwellings, and in quiet reſting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Behold here the ſenſe of the Apoſtle upon the words, where there is not a ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the paucity of ſuch as ſhall be ſaved, and doubtleſs it were an act of great teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to bow or wreſt the Text further than the very matter doth declare, or wider than the Prophets and Apoſtles have conceived of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But can you ſhew by ſome other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture, (for without this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity I know you attempt nothing) what muſt be underſtood by <hi>Joſuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> and why onely the little ones, the reſt being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, ſhould poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Canaan?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is no doubt but theſe two were preſerved to be witneſſes of thoſe wonderful deliverances, which God had vouchſafed to that unthankful people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they onely had the courage amongſt all the Spies, to undertake the extirpation of the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> but if we raiſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a higher conſideration, ſeeing that thoſe tranſactions pointed to the times of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62319:13"/> the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> it will be no impropriety to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <hi>Joſuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> were Types and adumbrations of the paucity of thoſe, who upon the firſt coming of our Saviour, ſhould believe in him, notwithſtanding the maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God was refulgent in him by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent atteſtation of miracles: which very thing, thoſe ſevere comminations againſt that ſtubborn and contumacious people do ſeem to import: <hi>For,</hi> ſaith God in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>Numbers, all thoſe men which have ſeen my glory, and my miracles which I did in Egypt, and in the wilderneſs, and have tempted me now theſe ten times, and have not hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to my voice: ſurely they ſhall not ſee the Land which I ſwore unto their fathers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any of them that provoked me ſee it.</hi> And a little after, he excepteth <hi>Joſuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> and all thoſe under the age of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years. Of which thing God complaineth in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (which place alſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> citeth in the tenth to the <hi>Romanes) I have ſpread out my hands all the day to a rebellious people.</hi> S. <hi>John</hi> alſo in the beginning of his Goſpel ſaith, <hi>He came unto his own, but his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive by theſe two (for as it is written, <hi>In the mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes every truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed</hi>) the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Diſciples of our Lord are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignified, who as they did teſtifie of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62319:13"/> wonders and miracles, ſo did they chiefly bear record of his Reſurrection. For ſo our Lord himſelf ſaith to his Apoſtles, <hi>Ye ſhall bear witneſs of me through the utmoſt parts of the earth.</hi> But now I expect to hear what you can ſay concerning the poſterity of them that ſell in the wilderneſs, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in this alſo is comprehended a great myſtery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould indeed have little to anſwer to this matter, had not S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that great Revealer of hidden things, opened a way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. For the Apoſtle in the eleventh to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> doth plainly propheſie that, <hi>Thoſe branches which were cut off through unbelief, ſhall through Faith be reingrafted.</hi> What elſe doth this ſignifie but that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of them that periſhed in the deſart, ſhall have acceſs into the Land of Promiſe? was not all <hi>Judea</hi> after the death of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour turned into a ſolitude? were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all them that had ſeen Chriſt, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by war, famine, or peſtilence? yet their generations, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſes, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into his Kingdom. In confirmation whereof, he doth accomodate the predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Prophets, and thus unfoldeth them to the preconſolation of the Gentiles. <hi>For I would not, Brethren, that ye ſhould be ignorant of this myſtery (leſt you ſhould be wiſe in your own concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>) that blindeneſs in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62319:14"/> part is happened to Iſrael, until the fulneſs of the Gentiles be come in, and ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved, as it is written: There ſhall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from</hi> Jacob. <hi>For this is my co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enant with them when I ſhall take away their ſins.</hi> Which words in the original are ſomewhat different; but it ſeems the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle followed the tranſlation of the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint,</hi> in which tranſlation the words are not ſo much conſidered as the ſenſe. Theſe things alſo <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Jeremiah,</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> do promiſe to the <hi>Iſraelites, that he will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them out of all Nations, and from the ends of the earth, that he will cleanſe them with pure water and purge them from all their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and give them a new heart, and a new ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To the other things I readily aſſent, but I do not ſufficiently underſtand what is meant by the Deliverer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſhew you my <hi>Caelius:</hi> This place is diverſly expounded, but the words of the Apoſtle are plain enough; for when he ſaith, <hi>he ſhall come,</hi> it is liquid he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of ſomewhat yet to come: and when he ſaith, <hi>the Deliverer ſhall come,</hi> whom can you ſuppoſe to be meant, but Jeſus Chriſt the onely Saviour and Redeemer of mankind? eſpecially when he addeth, <hi>out of Sion,</hi> that is, out of the very Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62319:14"/> whom this Prophecie doth belong. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome Holy and great man was to be ſent from God, for the inſtauration of a collapſed Church, and the replantation of an extinguiſhed Religion, this doth not at all ſeem different from the cuſtom of God. For when things are even deſpaired of, and grown deſperate, he then uſeth (as the Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi> ſpeaks) to raiſe up ſome <hi>Elias</hi> before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord, <hi>and he ſhall turn the heart of the Fathers to the Children, and the heart of the Children to their Fathers:</hi> that is, he will congregate and convert the hearts of thoſe Children to the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> whoſe Fathers have worſhipped him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And that this ſhould be performed by <hi>Elias</hi> was the opinion of <hi>Orig n, Theodoret, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm by that ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>When Elias comes he ſhall reſtore all things.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in my judgement, <hi>Paul</hi> in that place means none other but Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But was not Chriſt already come when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote? wherefore then doth he ſay, <hi>he ſhall come?</hi> What coming doth he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe? his firſt appearing to ſuffer death for us, or his laſt coming to judgement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> when he purpoſeth to deſcribe unto us by whom Antichriſt ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62319:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62319:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62319:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62319:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62319:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62319:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62319:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62319:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62319:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62319:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62319:20"/> and by what weapons he ſhould be overcome, after that for a time, he had proudly advanced himſelf againſt Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Chriſt, he thus writeth: <hi>Then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſs of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> In which words four things are decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us. That Antichriſt ſhall be dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by whom he ſhall be brought to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by what weapons, and laſtly that the Lord himſelf ſhall come in Perſon againſt this enemy, ſhall ſubdue him, and ſcatter all his forces; &amp; this ſhall be the means of that accompliſhment. Whatſoever is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, was firſt hidden, and whatſoever is brought to light is made manifeſt: Antichriſt for a long time hath lyen hid like a wolf in ſheeps cloathing: and ſtill had been unmani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, had not the appearance of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to reveal him: by whoſe coming again alſo he ſhall be utterly overthrown. But in the mean time, it behoves us to fight man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully under Chriſt our King and leader, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this adverſary and all his adherents: and leaſt we ſhould faint or be diſcouraged, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> aſſureth us he ſhall be delivered into our hands, <hi>And the Lamb ſhall overcome them, for he is Lord of Lords and King of kings, and they that are with him, are called, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and faithful.</hi> But with what weapons?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62319:20"/> with thoſe wherewith men go out to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel? No, but with <hi>the Spirit of his mouth, and the brightneſs of his coming.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I apprehend you, <hi>with the ſword of the Spirit,</hi> which is the word of God, that is, with arguments taken out of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Scriptures, which he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I deny not but the adverſaries of Chriſt may be fought withall, and brought to deſtruction by other weapons, but <hi>Paul</hi> telleth us, that Antichriſt ſhall be put to flight <hi>by the Spirit of his mouth,</hi> to exag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerate the power of Chriſt, who is able to vanquiſh his enemies by the breath of his noſtrels. <hi>For his Spirit,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>is an over flowing ſtream,</hi> he is alſo <hi>a conſuming fire,</hi> and Chriſt Jeſus is the brightneſs of this fire, at whoſe appearance the enemies vaniſh, as the night and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is diſperſed by the approch of the ſun.</p>
               <p>Now if the tyranny of Antichriſt, muſt be aboliſhed by the Spirit of the mouth of our Saviour before his laſt coming to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> foretelleth, ſaying, <hi>And the ten horns which thou ſaweſt upon the beaſt, theſe ſhall hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and ſhall burn her with fire.</hi>) That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel may be preached in all the Kingdoms of the earth; another coming of Chriſt muſt yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62319:21"/> be enquired after: and this is that coming by which he hath begun to reſtore the preaching of the Goſpel, to enlighten the underſtandings of them that ſate in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; to confirm them by his Spirit. We know well under how much blindneſs and ignorance the whole world, in former ages, hath been kept, contiguous almoſt to the very times of the Apoſtles. For as ſoon as their embaſſage was ended, the ravenous wolves begun to enter into the fold of Chriſt (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) not ſparing the flock. Thus by degrees the true Chriſt was taken out of the world, and a ſuppoſititious Chriſt laid in his room, in the holy place, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God eſtabliſhed in faith, not founded upon any material baſis. In which temple he ſitteth, and <hi>exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power and ſigns and lying wonders, and with all de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs in them that periſh; becauſe they received not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved.</hi> For they who ſhut their ears that they may not hear the truth, it is no wonder that they delight in lies. And when ſalvation is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them that believe the truth, they that delight in lies may juſtly fear damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If I underſtand you rightly, you inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that as the abſence of the Goſpel doth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62319:21"/> ſignifie the abſence of Chriſt, (for where his word is preached, where his voice is heard there is Chriſt) ſo by the return and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Goſpel is to be underſtood an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other coming of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Rightly taken; but I proceed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this middle coming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the 18. of <hi>Luke,</hi> Chriſt having propounded the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the unjuſt Judge and the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Widdow, ſaith of himſelf, <hi>When the Son of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n cometh, ſhall he find ſaith upon the earth?</hi> which cannot be underſtood of his laſt appearance, when the Goſpel being preached over all the earth, there will be an infinite multitude of believers. But that I may no longer detain your expectation, he then foretold this coming (if you heed the myſterie) when by his denouncing of judgement and deſtruction upon the Jews, he comforted and confirmed the minds of thoſe amongſt them who did or ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſaying, ſo reckon, <hi>that ye ſhall ſee me no more henc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>forth, until you ſhall ſay, bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</hi> Seeing therefore ſo much blindneſs is brought into the world, ſo many ſhadows of falſs Religion, and vails of falſe Doctrine: firſt into the Church by the decretals of the <hi>Popes,</hi> then by the fabulous ſtories of the <hi>Talmud,</hi> laſtly into other Nations by the lies of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in the Alchoran; it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62319:22"/> neceſſary, that Chriſt our King, by his moſt glorious coming, ſhould re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh all things in unity, that the learned may be directed to true wiſdom, and the ignorant inſtructed in true Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>One thing remaineth, which ſeemeth to me yet improved, you ſaid our Lord Chriſt had reſpect to his ſecond coming, when he told the <hi>Jews</hi> they ſhould ſee him no more, until with joyful acclamations they ſhould receive him as their Lord and King; which I conceive was then accompliſhed, when riding upon an Aſs towards Jeruſalem, they entertained him with that great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Two things are diligently to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: Firſt, whether our Saviour ſpake theſe words before thoſe acclamations, or afterwards: but let any man confer the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and he ſhall find they were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſpoken. Secondly, to whom theſe words were ſpoken. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke</hi> atteſteth that theſe words were ſpoken to the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> but let any man conſult the other <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> and he ſhall find, that he was afterward ſeen by the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> but he ſhall not find that ever they ſaid, bleſſed is he that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the name of the Lord. Nay they were ſo far from approoving theſe jubila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that it filled them with murmuring and objurgations, for in that day when the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62319:22"/> multitude followed him, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> ſheweth in the 12. Chap. of his Goſpel, that the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> ſaid within themſelves, do you not ſee that we prevail nothing? behold the whole world is gone after him. We muſt therefore ſeek after another Advent, and it will be that which we mentioned from the prophetical ſaying in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſhall be then accompliſhed, when the ſtragling and vagabond <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall infold themſelves into the Church of Chriſt, and when thoſe words of the people ſhall be fulfilled in their ſignification, <hi>Hoſanna to the ſon of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord, Hoſanna in the higheſt;</hi> for then according to the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I now plainly perceive that that place of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> is to be underſtood in a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe, and that upon the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be reſtored; and that I may briefly declare my mind, I ſuppoſe that all thoſe deſtructions that have happened to that people, and that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful blindneſs in which they have been captivated, did portend the univerſal cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which the world was to ſuffer under Antichriſt; and that this coming of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhall be as a reſurrection from ſin, a dereliction of our errours, and a converſion to the true Faith of Jeſus Chriſt, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62319:23"/> received delightful ſatisfaction in theſe doubts, I ſhall now propound ſome places in the New Teſtament, which make againſt this Opinion; and firſt theſe do occur the words of Chriſt himſelf: <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, for wide is the gate and broad is the way that leadeth to destruction, and many there are which enter in, but ſtrait is the door that leadeth to eternal life, and narrow is the way, and few there are that find it.</hi> Here Chriſt not obſcurely doth ſeem to ſignifie, that few ſhall be ſaved, but many ſhall be damned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is very excellently, and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken my <hi>Caelius,</hi> for indeed all things are not as they ſeem, neither are all things proved which appear to be ſo: ſome things are indeed ſuch as they ſeem to be as gold and ſilver, but other things though they appear true to the judgement of the ſence, yet are improperly ſo called, as tin and lytarge of gold mingled with gall and quick-ſilver have a ſemblance of true gold. Hypocrites which we call diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doe not they appear true, devout, and Holy? yet they are ſo far ſeperated and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from piety and true ſanctity by our Saviour Himſelf, that he called them painted ſepulchers, which are of beautiful outſides, but full of filth, and ſtink and rottennes within. He ſaith alſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62319:23"/> by their habit and behaviour they ſeem to be ſheep, but within they are ravening wolves. So on the other ſide moſt men are accounted irreligious and prophane, wicked and reprobated; are pointed at, hiſſed at, ſcoffed at, plundered, ſequeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, murthered as enemies to God and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and unworthy to injoy any ſhare in Gods creatures, yet theſe perſecuted men hold faſt the true Religion, and Faith in Chriſt. Our Saviour therefore in the 7. of <hi>John</hi> exhorteth us, <hi>not to judge by appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance but to judge righteous judgement.</hi> And in the 8. Chap. he reprehendeth the Phariſees that they <hi>judged after the manner of men,</hi> all is not gold that gliſters, the ſame thing may I ſay of this place by you alleadged; and perhaps they that extenuate the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the bleſſed, and leſſen the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> doe more oppoſe God, than they which amplifie and augment it. For if we ſearch into ſome things with a holy curioſity, the firſt appearances of them will vaniſh, from this very place this truth will be ſufficiently proved: For when a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain man aſked our Saviour, whether <hi>few or many ſhould be ſaved?</hi> Chriſt makes this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Strive to ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r in at the ſtrait gate, for many I ſay unto you will ſtrive to enter in, and ſhall not be able. When once the Master of the houſe is riſen up, and hath ſhut the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62319:24"/> door, and ye begin to ſtand without, and to knock at the door, ſaying, Lord, Lord, open unto us, and he ſhall anſwer and ſay unto you, I know you not whence you are; then ſhall ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſay, We have eaten and drunk in thy preſence, and thou hast taught in our ſtreets: but he ſhall ſay, I tell you, I know you not whence you are; depart from me all ye workers of iniquitie, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of teeth, when ye ſhall ſee</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the Prophets in the kingdom of God, and ye your ſelves thruſt out: and they ſhall come from the Eaſt and from the West, and from the North, and from the South, and ſhall ſit down in the kingdom of God, and behold, there are last, which ſhall be firſt, and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt which ſhall be laſt.</hi> I ſuppoſe you doubt not, but theſe words muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet if you ſhould ſcruple it, theſe words would reſolve you, <hi>We have eaten and drunk in thy preſence, and thou hast taught in our ſtreets.</hi> As if this muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage them, and entitle them to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, becauſe the Maſter of the houſe is of their own nation, and chiefly ſent to them: Which words ſome imagine to relate to the day of judgement; but to me they ſeem to refer to the firſt coming of Chriſt: and this will be manifeſt, to any man, that with diligence will examin the particulars, ſpoken of by our Saviour,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62319:24"/> wherefore Chriſt being aſked about the paucity of the elect, anſwers not to the queſtion, but directs his diſcourſe another way, leaſt he ſhould breed a remiſneſs, a negligence, a lazineſs in them to ſeek after the kingdom of God; and therefore he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth them to ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait-gate, before the Maſter of the houſe be riſen up, and ſhut it againſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What is this gate? and how to be ſhut?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You will plainly underſtand, what is meant by the gate, when I have ſhewed you, what it is to have the gate ſhut.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Proceed then to the handling of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>When we read that the Maſter of the houſe doth riſe, and ſhut the gate, we muſt underſtand thereby, the ſecret counſel of God upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> to blind them and harden them for a time, that they ſhould not confeſs him, and in a word, the ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the gate, is the rejection of the <hi>Jews</hi> for a ſeaſon, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Church of Chriſt. Which opinion is confirmed by thoſe words, by which he foretelleth, <hi>they ſhall come from all the four c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rners of the earth, and ſit down in the kingdom of God.</hi> And from the 14. of the <hi>Acts</hi> alſo, where <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> when they were come, and had gathered
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62319:25"/> the Church together, they rehearſed all that God had done with them, and how he had opened the door of Faith unto the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> Alſo by that which <hi>Luke</hi> ſaid before, that the door ſhould be ſhut after that the Maſter of the houſe was riſen up; but he roſe when Chriſt (who is that Maſter of the houſe, and Lord of the houſe of God his Church) had delivered himſelf from the power of death, from whence you ſee it follows that nothing elſe is underſtood by the <hi>ſtreight gate,</hi> but that ſhort intervail of time from the coming of Chriſt to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging, deſtruction, and deſolation of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> this alſo was foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> in the 9. Chap. <hi>And he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the covenant with many for one week, and in the midſt of the week he ſhall cauſe the ſacrifice and the oblation to ceaſe: and for the over-ſpreading of abominations he ſhall make it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſolate, even until the conſummation, and that determined ſhall be powred upon the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi> Again, our Saviour hath explained theſe words of the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>When you ſhall ſee</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>compaſſed about on every ſide, then know that her destruction is at hand:</hi> and a little after, <hi>This nation ſhall be greatly oppreſſed, and ſhall periſh by the edge of the ſword, till the times of the other nations be fulfilled.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But what are thoſe times?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62319:25"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall tell you, though perhaps o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than moſt men conceive: for Chriſt doth here intimate that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main under that blindneſs and calamity, tiil the other Nations of the world have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and embraced the Goſpel; which limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of time, is determined in the ſecret will of God: nor is it any other than what the words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> import: <hi>That blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in part is happened to Iſrael, till the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Gentiles become in.</hi> Now weigh the words, and obſerve whether this ſenſe of them be ſtrained, or detorted, or rather be not proper and genuine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They are indeed, onely the Apoſtle handleth them more at large.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let us therefore revolve and perpend the anſwer of Chriſt to the queſtion. You demand of me, <hi>whether few ſhall be ſaved?</hi> but I admoniſh you not to trifle away time in ſuch queſtions, but let there be a ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, a holy contention amongſt you with all celerity, to enter in at this door of my Goſpel: for the time is very ſhort, and when the hour of your rejection, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of your calamity approacheth, your complaints will become unprofitable, and your deſires to enter, fruſtrate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed: for the gate of Salvation ſhall be barred up, and the faculties of faith cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and ſtifled. Seek not, O ye <hi>Jews,</hi> with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62319:26"/> anxiety to know how few of you belong to the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> but with a wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation run the race of Faith, that ye may belong to that Church, and it behooves you alſo to ſet out early, if ye believe theſe words of mine, by which I provoke and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you to newneſs of life, and publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denounce and declare unto you the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Kingdom of God. Now if we believe the ſenſe of theſe words to be the ſame with thoſe of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> which you objected to me, which cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſeeing in both places there is mention of the narrowneſs of the gate, there that place in <hi>Matthew</hi> cannot reaſonably be underſtood of the number of the Elect, for if in that paſſage of <hi>Luke,</hi> nothing be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended but a premonition of that ſhort pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of time, in which the <hi>Jews</hi> had a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie by Faith, to attain the Kingdom of Chriſt, although the number of them was very ſmall which then ſhould believe, yet you muſt needs grant me, that thoſe things mentioned by our Saviour in the other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, muſt onely be referred to the Nation of the <hi>Jews:</hi> of which people few indeed did enter by the True Gate <hi>Chriſt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus,</hi> and very many by the ſecret purpoſe of God being excluded, remained without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The force of your reaſons doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline me to aſſent; and the rather, becauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62319:26"/> it hath been obſerved of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> that it is his peculiarity to deliver thoſe things clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſtinctly, which in the other Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts are related more obſcurely, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this is the gift of an elegant, and the duty of a perſpicuous Writer. I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for brevity ſake but in one example: <hi>Matthew</hi> writeth that the two theeves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween whom our Lord was crucified, uſed the ſame exprobations towards him, as did the Chief Prieſts, Scribes and Elders; but <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith onely one of them uſed contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious language againſt him; <hi>And one of the malefactours which were hanged, railed on him, ſaying, If thou be Chriſt, ſave thy ſelf and us: but the other anſwering, rebuked him, ſaying, Doſt not thou fear God, ſeeing thou art in the ſame condemnation? and we indeed juſtly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds, but this man hath done nothing amiſs.</hi> And although this be manifeſt, yet I would know if there be not another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of thoſe words of the <hi>narrovv vvay,</hi> and the <hi>narrow gate,</hi> if peradventure ſome man ſhould remain unſatisfied with this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is indeed <hi>Caelius;</hi> for when a place of Scripture is aſſumed to the proof of ſome falſe opinion, it may rather admit of any ſenſe, than that whereby it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the confirmation of that errour?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62319:27"/> will therefore redeem this place from the countenancing of an erroneous opinion, and accomodate it to the illuſtration and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment of truth. Firſt it is a matter acknowledged and requires no proof, that by the contumacie and fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> we are all conceived and born in original ſin, that confeſſion which <hi>David</hi> maketh of himſelf, is appliable to all the ſons of <hi>Adam; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive me.</hi> And it is no leſs evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that if any man be juſt, if any man be holy, he ought thankfully to confeſs that theſe ſtreams of ſanctitie, theſe divinations of righteouſneſs, do ſlow from that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Goodneſs <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> by a new and divine regeneration: <hi>For of his fulneſs have we received</hi> (that are members of his body) <hi>even grace for grace.</hi> Our Saviour in the words doth propound unto us two doors and two ways, one broad and wide, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrait and narrow; that, as leading to deſtruction; this unto eternal happineſs. But what elſe can we imagine this way of deſtruction to be, but the corrupt nature of mankind, and the proclivity of our wills to all errour and unrighteouſneſs? and what can be meant by the narrow way to Life, but the obſervation of the Commandments, and a ſincere imitation of our Lord Chriſt, who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62319:27"/> for he ſaith, <hi>If ye will have life, keep my Commandments.</hi> Alſo in another place, <hi>If any man will come after me, let him deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf, and let him take up his croſs and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is a very religious interpretation which you have given of theſe two ways, yet one thing doth not a little move me, that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Many enter in at the gate which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adeth to deſtruction, but few find that way which leadeth to Life:</hi> which argueth, that a ſmall number onely ſhall be ſaved, and the greater number ſhall incur everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting condemnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let me <hi>Caelius</hi> for a while interrogate thee, and do thou make anſwer, this way perhaps may facilitate the iſſue of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>With much willingneſs, for this hath been a cuſtom in diſputation deduced even from <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You have already granted that (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I be miſtaken) this broad way doth ſignifie and imply, the depraved nature of lapſed man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I do confeſs it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And that by this narrow gate, this difficult paſſage is meant, the precepts of God, the way of tribulation and calamitie, which was the path our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did walk in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62319:28"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To this alſo you have had my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I deſire you now to tell me, what can enter in at this broad gate, or rather, what you ſuppoſe it is to enter in at this broad and wide gate, but as I ſaid before, to be made and born of the corrupt matter of the old <hi>Adam?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That truly is my Opinion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Do you conceive that all men none excepted, or ſome men onely are obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to this neceſſitie of ſinning?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>All men, Chriſt Jeſus the Authour and Finiſher of our ſalvation excepted, who is therefore by S. <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>the Second A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and <hi>the New man: For as by the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of one man, ſin was propagated unto all men, ſo by the righteouſneſs of one man, all they that believe ſhall be made perfect,</hi> Rom. 5. Our Saviour alſo in S. <hi>John</hi> telleth us, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is born of the fleſh, is fleſh.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaith, <hi>I know that nothing in me, that is, in my nature, is good; for by nature we are all the ſons of wrath.</hi> Which places, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable others, do perſpicuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the impuritie of the nature of man: that I may ſay nothing of all thoſe inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections, violent concupiſcences, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinorous actions, &amp; hainous offences which are produced as the deadly poiſonous fruit of this corrupt tree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62319:28"/>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Your anſwer, <hi>Caelius,</hi> is very ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and oppoſite. What is it, think you, to find out this way, and this gate that leadeth to Life?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Doubtleſs to find out Chriſt, who is the <hi>Way,</hi> and the <hi>Door,</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing all other tranſitorie pleaſures, and fugitive comforts, to flie to him, and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him by right believing and well living.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But who entreth at this gate having nature onely for his guide, or how many follow Chriſt onely by the light of reaſon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>None alas, not one. For nature, as I have ſaid, being the way to death, whither can it lead us but to deſtruction?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Do all men therefore, following the conduct of nature, ſlide into death, and tumble into condemnation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This I have already granted without any heſitation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Our Lord Chriſt, then, when he ſaid <hi>many,</hi> underſtood <hi>all,</hi> and when he ſpake of a <hi>few,</hi> he meant <hi>none.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot gainſay it, I have granted the antecedent, and the conſequence is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable: but why did our Saviour rather ſay <hi>many</hi> and <hi>few,</hi> than <hi>all</hi> and <hi>none?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>In this we may contemplate the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and lenity of our ever bleſſed Saviour, who did ſo apportion and contemperate his ſayings, that neither theſe ſhould ſink into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62319:29"/> deſperation, nor they be lifted and puffed up to arrogance and oſtentation: it pleaſed him therefore to ſay <hi>many,</hi> not <hi>all,</hi> that he might qualifie the rigour and ſeverity of the matter, by the gentleneſs and mildneſs of ſpeech (for if he had ſaid <hi>all,</hi> he had preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated infirm and timorous conſciences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſperation) and with the ſame holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration he pronounced <hi>few</hi> ſhould find the narrow way: For had he ſaid <hi>none,</hi> he would have ſeemed to preclude and antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate all hope of all Salvation: thus by a moſt wiſe temperance and diſpoſition of ſpeech, he reflecteth to us our pravity and miſery, when he ſaith <hi>many,</hi> and when he ſaith <hi>few,</hi> he leaveth us not altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of hope, which is our heavenly via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Who then ſhall be ſaved?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>When the Maſter himſelf had affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it was more eaſie for a Camel to paſs through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God, preſently the Diſciples felt within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a conſternation of mind, and being ſuddenly ſtruck with an inward conflict of fear and wonder, they enquired as you now do, <hi>who then ſhall be ſaved?</hi> to which que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion he returned this conſolatory anſwer: <hi>To man this is impoſſible, but to God nothing is impoſſible:</hi> and thus he taught, that one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62319:29"/> and the ſame thing might be, and might not be: by the Divine aſſiſtance it might be accompliſhed, by the powers of nature it could not be effected. And this is it of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo glorifieth, <hi>through Christ,</hi> (of whom I receive my ſtrength) <hi>I am able to do all things:</hi> and in this ſenſe alſo we muſt underſtand the yoke of Chriſt to be eaſie, and his burthen light: light and eaſie to grace, grievous and burthenſom to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You conjoyn and expound theſe things moſt aptly, and as I apprehend, our Saviour in theſe ſayings made uſe of thoſe figures which the <hi>Grecians</hi> do call an Hypocoriſm, and an Hyperbole, the one ſpeaking of a thing with divination and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation; the other with incredible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement and amplification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Rightly obſerved: for ſuch extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are very much uſed in ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and ſometimes alſo in the Holy Scriptures: as for example, when <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the <hi>Romanes</hi> of the contumacy of the <hi>Jews: What</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if ſome of them have not believed?</hi> he ſaith ſome of them; when ſome of them onely had believed (a remnant ſelected out of the reſt) and all the other, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, were blinded. The ſame figure he alſo uſeth in the fifth to the <hi>Romanes: For as by one mans diſobedience
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62319:30"/> many were made ſinners: ſo by the obedience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</hi> I doubt not but you perceive in both theſe places, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt extenuation, when he ſaith, <hi>ſome of them did not believe,</hi> and many are dead; for he had ſaid before, that all were dead in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Theſe things being thus clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it is plain to all underſtanding, that our Saviour in this ſimilitude of <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>gates,</hi> underſtood nothing of the Multitude or Paucity of ſuch as ſhould be ſaved. And that you may more fully perceive, that our Lord in that place of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſpake not of the life to come ſimply and abſolutely, or meant any thing of the laſt end of men, ſuppoſe him to have ſaid thus, <hi>many</hi> ſhall come to deſtruction, but <hi>few</hi> ſhall find life, or <hi>many</hi> ſhall walk in that way which leads to everlaſting death, but <hi>few</hi> ſhall find the way to eternal life, here the way we ſee is not the end: And having made mention of the way, he doth admoniſh us of our humane imbecillity, and reduceth to memory our preſent miſery: that deſpairing of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing our own weakneſſes, we might have recourſe to the refuge of his goodneſs and clemency. For who that is grown to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity of years (not to ſpeak any thing of our impure beginnings) unleſs afflictions compel him, grace regenerate him, and the Spirit of God renew him, doth turn into
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62319:30"/> that troubleſom and unpleaſant way of the croſs? who hath an affiance in, and who is ſo inflamed with the love of God, as being ſecure of the life preſent and that to come, doubteth of nothing, is ſolicitous after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? who is careful of his neighbours good and goods, as of his own, and who is equally ſenſible of his loſſes, croſſes, and afflictions, as of his own? who is ſo careful to honour God in the riches of his Mercy, as he is induſtrious and plotting and toyling to inrich his own family, and to enamil o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a fugitive felicity? yet this the Law, this the Prophets, this the Lord himſelf with ſtrict ſeveritie hath commanded us: <hi>Thou ſhalt love God above all things, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> What ſhall I ſay then? Is the whole Maſs of mankind created to deſtruction? and are we all excluded Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven through the infirmitie of our nature? God forbid! for our Heavenly Father to all our ſpiritual evils, languiſhings, and relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hath applied the medicine of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mercy, for he himſelf teſtifieth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>He ſent not his Son into the world to condemn the world, but that the world through him ſhould be ſaved.</hi> From hence <hi>Paul</hi> alſo proclaimeth it, <hi>He ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t up all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, that he might have mercy upon all.</hi> Let us therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out with the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Miſerable man that I am, who ſhall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62319:31"/> deliver me from this body of death?</hi> and let us ſubjoyn alſo our acknowledgement with thankſgiving to him who doth deliver us, ſaying, <hi>I give thanks unto God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> You ſee now my <hi>Caelius,</hi> the perverſeneſs of their concluſion who thus argue, <hi>Few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nter in at the ſtrait gate,</hi> therefore <hi>few ſh ll be ſaved.</hi> And now you apprehend the ſafetie and ſweetneſs of this concluſion, <hi>Few find the way which leadeth to Eternal Life,</hi> therefore God doth ſpread, dilate, and diffuſe his grace, otherwiſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man muſt altogether inherit corruption, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>If thou ſhouldſt be extream to mark what is done amiſs, O Lord, who is able to ſtand before thee.</hi> Here now is the door opened into that large field of the mercy of God, when through his benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and their faith, he conſerveth the guilty. That is a true ſaying, <hi>Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the Lavv, to do them;</hi> But this is no leſs true, <hi>That Chriſt Jeſus died for the ungodly, and vvas made a curſe for us, that vve ſhould be freed from the curſe of the Lavv:</hi> ſo that we are both accurſed and bleſſed, execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by nature, but ſanctified by grace; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed in <hi>Adam,</hi> but holy and happy in Chriſt, to whom he honour and adoration for evermore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To the Lord Chriſt the Authour and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62319:31"/> Life of our life be all praiſe and glory, that by his wiſdom hath brought to paſs, that thou haſt ſo clearly illuſtrated this moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult place, that there remaineth no doubt, no ſcruple, no heſitation. Now I perceive how aptly one truth agreeth with another, and what a hollow and unſound reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made between truth and falſhood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If any other places of Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any appearing contrariety to this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, name them <hi>Caelius,</hi> that before dinner I may give anſwer unto, and vindicate them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall perform it with great willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with the beſt aid of my memory, I ſhall chooſe ſuch places as are moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of explication in this matter. And firſt I will inſtance in that Parable of the Sower, whereby our Lord doth inſinuate unto us that a remnant onely ſhall be ſaved, for as it is written in the thirteenth of <hi>Matthevv,</hi> the fourth part onely of the ſeed did fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, the reſt periſhing by divers accidents. Wherefore I covet to hear what you can produce in anſwer to this allegation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It is the trueſt and the juſteſt office of an Interpreter to expend, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the end, purpoſe, and intent of the Speaker. This obſervation is neceſſary in all emergencies, but then eſpecially uſeful when we examine the ſayings, and Parables of our Saviour, becauſe not all can anſwer
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62319:32"/> in every reſpect to the purpoſe of the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. This ſome have attempted but with ſmall ſucceſs. Let us therefore content our ſelves to enquire out the meaning and ſcope of the place, for in that is contained all the doctrine and inſtruction that can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the ſpeaker. For the ſimilitude it ſelf, and the explication of it muſt be applied to the ſcope and intent, not the intent to the ſimilitude, for by ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous accomodation, many abſurdities would follow. In this collation therefore our Lord Chriſt intending to ſhew us all thoſe impediments, by which we are chiefly withdrawn from the worſhip of God, (the principal part whereof is the hearing and the practiſing of the Word preached) bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth a ſimilitude from the Sower, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth up thoſe things that retard and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth of the ſeed, and doth acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate them to the Heavenly ſeed, which is the word of God. Then he nameth three general impediments; the devil, tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the cares of this life; and at leaſt with one of theſe is every man tormented and perſecuted, yet doth the word of God take root, and bring forth fruit in a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In what place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>In the good and fertile ground.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But which is that good ground, if
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62319:32"/> three parts be ſcattered, one by the way, another upon a rock, and a third part falleth among thorns?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Even that ground by the way ſide, that rock, and that thorny place, when that Spiritual Husbandman ſhall have driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fowls of the air, ſhall have removed that rock, and burnt up thoſe thorns. Did not <hi>Paul</hi> fall by the way? did not <hi>Peter</hi> daſh upon this rock? and was not <hi>Matthevv</hi> choaked with theſe thorns? yet <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an elect Veſſel, and the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles; Peter</hi> the chief Paſtour to the <hi>Jevvs,</hi> a Feeder of Chriſts ſheep and lambs; and <hi>Matthevv</hi> both an Apoſtle and an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt. Therefore the drift of that ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude was onely to teach the ſucceſs and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of that Heavenly Doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply any thing of the final condition of the Saints or reprobates: although we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from this very ſimilitude, and thoſe things that follow in the ſame chapter, that the number of the Elect ſhall be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe the Paucity hath reſpect unto the <hi>Jevvs,</hi> of whom, as we ſhewed before, were to be gathered out from all parts of the world, and preſerved as the ſeminary of the Kingdom of Chriſt. This alſo may be gathered from that moſt plentiful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the good ground (which was the Apoſtles and the other Diſciples.) Alſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62319:33"/> from the grain of Muſtard-ſeed, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be the leaſt of all ſeeds, when it is grown, it is the greateſt among herbs, and becometh a tree, ſo that the birds of the air come and lodge in the branches thereof: Alſo from the leaven, which though it be little, yet being hid among many mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of meal, it leaveneth the whole lump: all which collations and reſemblances do lively expreſs the power and energie of the Word of God, and are as ſo many Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Manifeſtations of the greatneſs and largeneſs of the <hi>Church Triumphant;</hi> but if any man ſhould reply, that by this ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſour ſorts of hearers are demonſtrated unto us, yet were it inconſequent to infer from hence a Paucity of Believers. Let us ſuppoſe an hundred Auditours, ten where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the devil ſnatching away the ſeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unprofitable; Again ten others fall off by a perſecution, ſpring up againſt the Word; Laſtly, ten more revolt through love of riches, now the other ſeventy bring forth good fruit, ſome fifty, ſome ſixty, ſome an hundred fold, ſome ſix hundred fold, and by this reaſon do not all things fitly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond, and is not the compariſon firm?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It will be firm indeed: but then the diviſion of the hearers are not diſtributed into equal parts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Our Saviour himſelf hath not ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62319:33"/> them, nor commanded any ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, but onely ſaid, thus and thus the ſeed fell. And what groſs malignity would it be in us, to wreſt the words of a merciful Saviour, to a rigid interpretation? For if this doth not happen amongſt us in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſowing and husbandry, that the greater part of the ſeed doth utterly periſh, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we muſt not imagine ſo of the Heavenly ſeed, ſowed plentifully in our hearts by the liberal hand of that Spiritual Husbandman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Truly <hi>Maynardus,</hi> according to your premonition, I judge the Scriptures ſhould be interpreted according to the context, ſcope, and meaning of the ſpeaker: and what you have anſwered concerning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of our Lord in theſe Parables, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove as very proper and genuine. And with the opening of theſe places, I am ſo affected, fitted, and enabled to underſtand others, that I will onely object one or two, and pretermit the reſt, yet are they very few. I come then to that place which makes moſt men of that malignant opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſalvation of mankind. I mean the place which is at the concluſion of the two Parables; one of the Vine-yard, the other of the Marriage of the Kings Son, where it is in both places moſt clearly ſaid, <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay right, when you call it a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62319:34"/> opinion, I will add an envious and a dangerous opinion, driving men violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into deſperation, and ſuch errours they might ſoon and eaſily avoid, if they would obſerve that Law of interpretation which I mentioned before; for in the Goſpel, if all the ſayings of our Lord Chriſt were through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed, it would be confeſſed that the greater part of them had reference to the <hi>Jews,</hi> for as he himſelf witneſſeth, to them chiefly was he ſent; <hi>I was not ſent but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo in the 15. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the truth of God, to confirm the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made unto the Fathers.</hi> Therefore he was diligent with all care to perform his miniſtery, in calling them, teaching them, exhorting them, warning them, healing their ſick, affecting them with benefits, convincing them with miracles: for all which bowels of compaſſion towards them, they afflicted him, reviled him, crucified him, killed him, all which things he would undergo: firſt, that he might accompliſh his embaſſage, then that the benefit of his death and the glorie of his reſurrection might redound to all nations and people that ſhould receive with Faith theſe glad tidings of their Salvation. For I do not deny but the Doctrine of the Son of God
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62319:34"/> rightly and faithfully received, to be the Doctrine of all times, ages, places, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but this I would, that thoſe Texts and ſayings which are accomodated to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, places, and times, ſhould not be applied to the univerſality of men, and time. For not all things belong to all men after one and the ſame manner, as they are commanded, and ſpoken to ſome: If you deſire an example, take that of the young man, who deſired leave to burie his Father, to whom Chriſt anſwereth, <hi>Follow thou me, and let the dead burie their dead.</hi> Therefore hereafter let none take care to ſee their friends well buried; I will not care for the dead when either the glorie of God, or the neceſſity of the living command my aſſiſtance. Our Saviour bad them that were cured of the Leproſie to ſhew themſelves to the Prieſts: Therefore muſt they now that are healed of the itch or Leproſie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the Prieſts?</p>
               <p>I know ſome men from hence would au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe private Confeſſion, or rather confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for with ſuch fooliſh, and impious Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories they indeavour to obſcure the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, it was an argument of Divine power, and an evident teſtimonie of the obedience of Chriſt, who came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but to fulfil the Law, for it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid in the Law, that the Prieſt ſhould
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62319:35"/> judge of the leper. The Lord alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the rich Man to <hi>ſell all his goods and give them to the poor and to follow him;</hi> that ſaying very much troubled him and made him ſad, yet perhaps he afterwarwards put it in execution. And if he did not, he ought to have done it, in obedience to the command of ſo good and gratious a Maſter, it will be ſufficient for us to have ſuch a preparation of mind, that if the welfare of our brethren, and the glorie of the Lord require it, to part with all things yea life it ſelf, but this being a ſingular injunction, and commanded onely to one man, doth not bind the generality of men; ſo that they ſhould neglect their eſtates, or impend all their wealth upon the poor, any more than they are bound to ſacrifice their ſons becauſe God commanded <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to ſuch an obedience, and therefore becauſe our Lord ſaid unto the <hi>Jews, that many are called, but few are choſen,</hi> we muſt not generally extend and ſtretch theſe words to all times and perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You mean (if I underſtand you right) that thoſe ſayings were meant of the <hi>Jews</hi> of thoſe times, and ſolely to be appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, of whom many by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and afterwards many were called by the Lord himſelf, but few were choſen, namely Apoſtles, Diſciples, and ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62319:35"/> as the Holy Scriptures do witneſs: theſe were the little flock to whom Chriſt did Miniſter that conſolation in <hi>Luke,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Fear not little flock, for it is the will of your Father to give you a Kingdom,</hi> this is that remnant of which <hi>Paul</hi> in the 11, to the <hi>Rom.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Even ſo then there is at this time a Remnant, according to the election of grace;</hi> theſe are that ſeed of whom alſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Except the Lord of Sabboth had left us a ſeed, we had been as Sodom, and been made like unto Gomorrha.</hi> In all which places the paucity of the <hi>Jews</hi> of thoſe times which ſhould be ſaved is not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You take my meaning right, and you have very aptly connumerated thoſe places of Scripture. Thoſe that do detort that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Saviour ſhould obſerve that all thoſe parables in the 20, 21, and 22. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Matthew</hi> do contain the rejection of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the calling of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> In confirmation of this truth weigh thoſe words in the firſt ſimilitude in the 20 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they murmured againſt the good man of the houſe, ſaying, <hi>Theſe laſt have wrought but one hour, and thou haſt made them equal unto us, which have born the burthen and the heat of the day.</hi> And it is manifeſt, that after the reſurrection of Chriſt, theſe <hi>Jews</hi> did make complaints: and when <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62319:36"/> the reſt of the Apoſtles preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to them that were without, they held it an unjuſt thing, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be made equal to them, the ancient, and Holy people of God: this is plain to be ſeen both in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, and alſo in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> In the ſame parable alſo theſe words, <hi>Take what is thine, and go thy way,</hi> do clearly imply the rejection of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and what is more manifeſt than that convertible Text? <hi>Thoſe that are laſt ſhall be firſt, and thoſe that are firſt ſhall be laſt.</hi> Who (I pray) are thoſe <hi>laſt made firſt,</hi> but the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alienated from the Common-wealth of Iſrael, and now preferred before the <hi>Jews?</hi> and who are thoſe <hi>firſt made laſt,</hi> but the <hi>Jews</hi> for a time rejected, till the fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> be come in? Then alſo thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhall be ſaved, as we have ſhewed before. Moreover, the Parable of the 21 Chapter cannot admit of doubt; and that in the 22. Chapter is ſo perſpicuous, that if in the firſt there poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly were any doubt to be raiſed, yet this would eaſily remove and diſſolve it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the ſame ſentence, <hi>Many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, few are choſen,</hi> is found alſo in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of that parable. Now that this ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude was by our Lord appropriated to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who can make a queſtion when he obſerves theſe words? <hi>The wedding is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62319:36"/> ready but they which were bidden are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: Go ye therefore into the high wayes, and as many as ye ſhall find bid to the marriage.</hi> This is the ſame which our Lord command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Diſciples, <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to all creatures. Mark</hi> the laſt Chapter. This <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> teſtifie in the <hi>Acts, It was neceſſarie, that the word of God ſhould firſt have been ſpoken to you: but ſeeing ye put it from you, and judge your ſelves unwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thie of everlaſting life, See, we turn to the Gentiles; for ſo hath the Lord commanded us.</hi> Now compare this of <hi>Paul</hi> with that of our Saviour, and you will find that one egge is not more like another. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They that were invited, were not worthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>You judge your ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie;</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Go out into the high waies Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We go out unto the Gentiles, for thus hath the Lord Commanded.</hi> But let us riſe to dinner, there is an importunate cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditour muſt alſo have ſome ſatisfaction. That which remaineth (which indeed is the moſt important matter) we will difer until the afternoon.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="part">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>THe ſerenity of the air, my <hi>Caelius,</hi> and this pleaſant face of heaven doe even invite us to forſake the houſe. With your allowance therefore we will repair to yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62319:37"/> ſummer-houſe, and ſpin out our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is moſt agreeable <hi>Maynardus</hi> for I prefer the benefit of your converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ſublunary contentments. It is now your part to proceed, and as the gravitie of the matter doth require, I ſhall lend you a very attentive ear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I will proceed, conditionally that you will interpoſe, when you doubt of any thing ſpoken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall moſt willingly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Firſt I will declare the firſt riſe and beginning of that opinion concerning the <hi>paucitie of the Elect.</hi> Secondly, I will prove by plain and ſolid arguments, <hi>the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude and Largeneſs of the</hi> CHURCH TRIUMPHANT. In the beginning, as by the ſubtle malice of the Devil, death got an enterance into the World; ſo by his artifice and emulation, this envious and narrow Opinion hath been advanced and diſſeminated; for this father of lies, this enemy of mankind, ſaw and collected by indubitable ſigns, that the Church of God was eſtabliſhed in mercy, as upon an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable foundation: and that by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, God would ſettle his heavenly Kingdom; which ſhould conſiſt of infinite multitudes of Citizens: therefore hath he endeavoured, and doth ſtill contrive by a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62319:37"/> thouſand deceits, temptations, and treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to coarctate, ſtraiten, and preclude the paſſage into that kingdom. Thus by crafty enticement he beguiled our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and had not the wiſdom and great goodneſs of God intervened, all mankind had periſhed in their fall. But no violence, no power, no fraudulencie of Hell can nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the eternal decrees of God. His pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe therefore hath ſtill taken effect, and in all ages his Church hath been enlarged according to the predetermination of his good pleaſure: nor could the ſeed of God be ſcattered and loſt by all the oppoſitions of the Devil. That Anti-God conſidereth this, and applies his malice to new ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems: amongſt others, ſpreads this opinion <hi>of the ſmall number of the Elect, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable multitude of the damned</hi> among thoſe that are commonly called the wiſer ſort of men. From hence came thoſe verſes,
<q>
                        <l>Omnibus in terris quae ſunt à Gadibus uſque</l>
                        <l>Ad Gangen, pauci dignoſcere poſſunt vera bona: —</l>
                     </q> Alſo,
<q>
                        <l>Rari quippe boni numero vix ſunt totidem,</l>
                        <l>Quot Thebarum portae, vel divitis oſtia Nili.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another Authour alſo ſaith, <hi>The number of fools is infinite,</hi> theſe words are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quoted as out of <hi>Salomon</hi> in his <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastes,</hi> yet let the Text be rightly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Cicero</hi> muſt own the ſaying; Another
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62319:38"/> ſaith, <hi>All things are full of folly.</hi> Which ſpeeches: fall from ſuch men who think none good, none wiſe, none happy but themſelves. <hi>Plato</hi> in his book to <hi>Phaedon</hi> the Philoſopher, is more moderate, for he ſaith, <hi>Few men are extreamly good or bad, but moſt men are of a midling iniquitie:</hi> ſo likewiſe the extremities of all things are few and rare, as very little or very great, very white or very black, very ſwift or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſlow, but the indifferencies, are many and frequent. Now if you compare the number of the beſt men with that of the tolerably good, this laſt number will infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely exceed the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is even as you ſay. And verily this Philoſopher hath ever ſeemed to me more Religious than the reſt. But thoſe others I take to be ſuch men, as a couple which were lately amongſt us, when they met in the ſtreet, and had ſaluted one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; quoth the one, I tell thee <hi>John,</hi> there are but two honeſt men in all our Citie: and I aſſure thee replied the other, I think <hi>George</hi> thou art one of them, and truly <hi>John</hi> (ſaith he) thou art the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They knibbled one another like horſes. But I return to that ſerpent, who by little and little rigled himſelf, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated into the judgement of wiſe men, and by ſubtile extenuations, and malicious
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62319:38"/> diminutions gave them to underſtand, that the mercy of God, and the goodneſs of God to mankind, was not ſo great as was ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined. That God was good and merciful, was undenyable truth; but withall he was juſt, and a moſt ſevere revenger of offences and tranſgreſſions. Two wayes he deviſed to inſtil this perſwaſion; one from witneſſes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other from ſignes and cauſes. His witneſſes were thoſe who wreſted the fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed places of Scripture, which by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God we have ſo far vindicated, that hereafter they will not be able to alledge the leaſt matter of moment in oppoſition. His cauſes are the actions and bad deeds of men, which that experienced deceiver doth uſe to term ſo. And theſe nets he ſpreadeth with ſuch diligent and cunning artifice, that truely it is no hard matter to fall into them, nay it is a moſt difficult thing to avoid them, for thus he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croacheth upon the underſtanding; Wilt thou know, O man the truth of thy ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or damnation, and not onely of thine but of all others? Contemplate the inclinations, the ſtudies, the meditations, the purſuits, the actions of men, which are the cauſes of eternal happineſs, or eternal miſery; if the actions be good, of ſalvation; if bad, of condemnation. Now look about thee, judge the trees by their fruits, and thou
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62319:39"/> wilt eaſily diſcern how few they are that keep the commandments; and obſerve the multiſarious parts of righteouſneſs: how ſmall and contemptible number there is of good men, how vaſt a multitude of wicked men and unjuſt. Wherefore diſpelling all doubts and heſitations thus conclude: If good works are the inerrable ſigns of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and wicked actions the infallible cauſes of everlaſting deſolation, it follows by unavoydable conſequence, <hi>That ſmall is the number of the Elect, infinite the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Reprobates.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>O old Serpent, O helliſh monſter compacted of malice and deceit! I am afraid, too many wiſe men of this world have been tutord and diſciplined by this Sophiſter, whom I have often heard to knit and interweave thus their Fallacies and Sophiſmes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you doubt it? there is nothing more ſure than they are taught and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him, who ſeperate themſelves from the Communion and fellowſhip of other Chriſtians, as if they onely were Religious and Holy, but all other men execrable, profane, and reprobates. For this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion had its firſt ſpring from the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, afterwards by degrees, it got a ſlide into the unwarie perſwaſion of Chriſtians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I make no doubt of that. But I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62319:39"/> would now know how to be unintangled from theſe fallacies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, I would grant all thoſe things, that God is moſt juſt, that no man perfectly worketh righteouſneſs, or fulfilleth the Law in all its requiſites: and therefore that by nature, or the obſervation of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, no man is juſtified. Eminent is that ſaying, <hi>There is none that doth good, no not one.</hi> Alſo <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is none good but God onely.</hi> But I would remember alſo that God the Father, hath transferred all our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, (which was his goodneſs) and the univerſal puniſhment due to our ſins upon the obedience of Chriſt, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> teacheth, <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed. All we like ſheep have gone aſtray, and have turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all.</hi> This alſo the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf teſtifieth, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> The Son alſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts it, <hi>I lay down my life for my ſheep.</hi> Then I would deny the antecedent of the connexed words.</p>
                  <p>I would anſwer, That good works are not the cauſes of Salvation, but the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, and his everlaſting mercy in Jeſus Chriſt, comprehended by faith. I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62319:40"/> would alſo anſwer, that wicked actions are not ſimply and abſolutely the cauſes of damnation, but diffidence, unbelief, and pertinacy. As the Lord ſaith in the 16. of <hi>John, The ſpirit muſt reprove the world of ſin, becauſe they did not believe in him.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>Through unbelief the branches are broken off;</hi> alſo, <hi>That God hath ſhut up all men under unbelief, that he might have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all, both Jews and Gentiles.</hi> And becauſe I have faith in God, and embrace his mercy, and am delighted in the Law of the Moſt High, though the appetite and vitious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the outward man, reſiſt and gainſay, yet I would conclude, that neither ſin, nor Law, nor the powers of Hell ſhould be able to condemn me. As <hi>Paul</hi> in many places witneſſeth: <hi>We believe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that man is juſtified by faith, not by the works of the Law. David</hi> likewiſe, in this placeth mans beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, when God imputes righteouſneſs to him without works: <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe ſins are forgiven, and whoſe iniquities are blotted out. Bleſſed is that man to whom God hath not imputed ſin.</hi> Laſtly, I would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that from the appearance of works, no infallible criterium could be grounded of our everlaſting condition, becauſe we are not ignorant that thoſe men that have been moſt dear to God, have collapſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in moſt preſumptious and dangerous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62319:40"/> ſins, who afterwards upon repentance, have been reſtored to eternal happineſs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought not to judge raſhly of the final eſtate of others, but leave them to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, either to ſtand or fall, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I approve your anſwer brother <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nordus,</hi> for it moſt rationally confutes the cavils of the adverſaries, and their miſtaken expoſitions, and ſolidly confirmeth our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. And hereafter by the aſſiſtance of God, I will thus repel the darts of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and elude the ſubtile arguments of ſome men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord teach thy hands to war that bows of ſteel may be broken by thine arms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. I conceive I have now ſufficiently ſhewed the firſt hatching of this barbarous opinion, and all its ſerpentine turnings and windings. It remains now that we proceed to the confirmation of our moſt ſalutiferous perſwaſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>You judge rightly, otherwiſe you may incur the ſame cenſure with <hi>Lactantius,</hi> who was ſaid very ſoundly to confute the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of his adverſaries, but very weakly to maintain and prove his own aſſertions. But in my judgement, theſe men ſeem ignorant of the duty of a prudent Oratour, neither do they fully underſtand the diſpoſure u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed by <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his Books of Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: For it is the part of a wiſe Oratour
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62319:41"/> (as <hi>Cicero</hi> teacheth us) to endeavour all he can, that that part of his Oration which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the refutation of his Opponent, be more firm, compact and pithy, than that which concerns his own Defence, to caſt all our darts againſt him; but if our own aſſertions be eaſier to be proved, and his harder to be overthrown, then it is an excellent courſe to endeavour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and withdraw the minds of men from the oppoſite defence, and to convert them to the favouring of our own. Which things being true, I ſee no reaſon why it ſhould be objected againſt him, that he laboured more in refutation, than in proof; for ſuch is the cauſe of Religion, that it muſt not be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the infirmity of humane argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſubminiſtration of reaſon, but muſt flouriſh in the embraces of an active Faith. <hi>Go ye into all the world</hi> (ſaith our great Maſter) <hi>and preach the Goſpel to every creature: he that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned. Paul</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>That a Biſhop ſhould be able by ſound Doctrine, both to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and convince the gainſay rs, Tit.</hi> 1. For there is no more required, but the ſincere and pure word of God, which to them that are ordained to eternal beatitude, is more ſure, firm and infallible, than principles and demonſtrations are to Geometricians. And
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62319:41"/> therefore if any man hath detected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed an erroneous opinion, he hath well performed his undertaking. I ſpeak not this, as though <hi>Lactantius</hi> had not confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed true Religion, as it was to be proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them who were ignorant of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or deſpiſed them. For when, in the firſt three Books, he confuted the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious errours of his adverſaries, then he falls upon the proof of Chriſtian Religion: in the next three Books, and in the ſeventh, he ſets down the true end of our Religion, and ſweetly invites men to purſue the reward of immortalitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſpeak of that Father, is very true, that he was to contend againſt ſuch as denied the authority of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, neither did they admit of Proofs deduced from that authority. But we who have to deal with ſuch men as reverence the Sacred Monuments of Truth, muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in a different manner. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore demonſtrate the <hi>Amplitude and Large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Church Triumphant,</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om four moſt firm and moſt clear topick places, and with as much brevity, as the reaſon of the matter will allow. Firſt, from the power of God: Secondly, from his wiſdom: Thirdly, from his mercy and goodneſs: and Laſtly, from Divine Teſtimonies. To begin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the firſt, I ſay, <hi>Caelius,</hi> that if we
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62319:42"/> ſhould grant the Church and Kingdom of God to be narrower, or leſs peopled than that miſerable Commonwealth of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, I fear, we ſhould derogate from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and majeſty of our Creatour and King. For the power and greatneſs of a King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not ſo much in wealth and treaſure, as in the multitude of his people, the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his territories, the extent of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and the vaſt number of his Subjects who pay him tribute, and are ſubject to his Dominion. How did the people of <hi>Rome</hi> ſwell to that greatneſs, but by the multitude of Kingdoms and variety of Nations which they ſubdued, and governed? from hence they were ſtiled the powerful <hi>Romanes,</hi> and Lords of the world. From hence their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate was called the <hi>Haven of Nations,</hi> the <hi>Refuge of Kings.</hi> For what is greatneſs, but an abundance of power and majeſty? and what is power but a facultie of protecting others, defending themſelves, and a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of the oppreſſed from the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an enemy? but if the enemy of God and man be better provided of ſubjects, than the King of Heaven, he is then more powerfull, and his greatneſs more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. But who was ever ſo prodigiouſly wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as to affirm the devil to be more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful than God? the work, than the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? the baſeſt ſervant, than the moſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62319:42"/> wealthy Lord? wherefore doth the Lord of Heaven delight himſelf in theſe Titles, <hi>King of kings, Lord of lords, the Mighty God, the Lord of Hoſts, Strong in battel;</hi> and the like?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Although the current of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe doth very much affect me; nor do I willingly hinder it; yet I cannot forbear for a while to ſtop it. Some man might here ſay, this alſo is a great argument of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the King of Heaven, in that he hath deſtinated the major part of mankind (who were all his enemies) to everlaſting baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This might be alledged of ſome Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who leaves no means unattempted, either through juſtice or oppreſſion, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his Empire; and ſuch a Tyrant is that old adverſary the devil. But to affirm this of our Heavenly King, who is our moſt law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soveraign, our common Father, who made us, and hath taken an everlaſting care to preſerve us, were moſt injurious, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and blaſphemous. Neither is that any right demonſtration of power, that a Prince deſtroyeth the greater part of his people, but on the contrary it is an invincible evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of power, when the greater number are by him preſerved. For the clearer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this: Suppoſe two Princes, one whereof without all Law or provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62319:43"/> ſave that of his own exorbitant will, ſought the ruine of his people, and bent all his intentions to deſtroy them: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſed all induſtry, care, and diligence (though they were ungrateful) to preſerve them, ſhould not the greateſt power be judged to be in him the Protector?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What if he preſerved but a greater part, would you ſuppoſe him to be a more powerful Prince than the other?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not? Truly both the more powerful, and alſo the more merciful; for if he could have ſaved all, he would have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not think ſo, where then is his juſtice? for without it, there can be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of virtue, for the puniſhment of, and his ſeverity unto a few, doth exalt and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his clemency to the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs it, but we muſt be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, leaſt whileſt we praiſe his clemency, and augment his power, we diminiſh his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. But if theſe attributes be equal in God, then the number of the bleſſed, and the number alſo of the damned are equal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Such an equality is not to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, where there is neither debt nor merit, here onely the true bounty, the free mercy of God are diſcerned: for God oweth to no man, and it is lawful for him to do what he
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62319:43"/> pleaſeth with his own creature, the work of his own hands, and faſhioned for his glory; unleſs that the nature of all men, eſpecially that of a Prince, ſhould be more propenſe to clemency and pardon, than addicted to puniſhment and revenge: as God himſelf witneſſeth of himſelf, ſaying, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gratious, long-ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and abundant in goodneſs and truth.</hi> Now no motive is ſo prevalent, as the promiſe of ſalvation, to win ſouls to God; nothing is ſo magnificent, ſo princelike, ſo highly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral, as to ſuccour the afflicted, to pardon the ſuppliant, and to deliver men from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: on the contrary, nothing is more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, vile, and deformed, than to make the higheſt cruelty to cohabite with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt power.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>If God loweth nothing to man, why is it ſaid in the 20. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe bid his Steward call the labourers, and give to every one their hire? Alſo our Lord Chriſt ſaith to thoſe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer reproach and perſecution for his Names ſake, <hi>Rejoyce and be exalted in joy, for I ſay unto you, great is your reward in Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord out of his meer goodneſs and benignity, calleth that a reward or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, which is the effect of his own li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, and this by the ſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l of that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is manifeſt; The good man of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62319:44"/> houſe went out to ſeek labourers, not they to ſeek him, as he ſaith in <hi>Iſaiah, I am found of them that did not ſeek me, I was made manifeſt to them that asked not after me.</hi> He calleth them, he hireth them, he ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, he ſendeth for them, and he pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them. Some acknowledge the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Maſter, and murmure not; others complain, uſing many objurgations, taxe him of unjuſtice, and boaſt their own works and day-labours, all theſe the Lord thus ſatisfieth, <hi>Friend, I do thee no wrong, didſt thou not agree with me for a penny? take what is thine, and be gone, I will give unto this last even as unto thee, is it not lawful to do what I will with mine own? a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t thou envious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am good and lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ral?</hi> What I pray thee, do all theſe things import but the bounty of the Maſter of the houſe? which is moſt plainly proved by thoſe words, <hi>that it was lawful for him to do with his own, as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt pleaſed him.</hi> For he now calleth thoſe things his, which before he called by the name of a hire, that we might underſtand his wonderful goodneſs, for he adorneth his own gifts with the name of a reward, that he might cheriſh and rowſe up our ſluggiſh natures to the lively performance of our duties. For otherwiſe, hath not the Lord ſtampt it as a Law, ſaying, <hi>when you have kept all the Commandments, ſay of your ſelves,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62319:44"/> You are but unprofitable ſervants, for you have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rformed but your duty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>What is there intended by the word <hi>penny?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The penny ſignifieth the Covenant which he hath made with us, offering to us life or death, honour or ignominy, felicity or miſery. All theſe things, Life, Honour, Felicity, are by his Fatherly indulgence promiſed to them that do not attribute them to their own works or merit, but to the proud, and ſuch as boaſt of their own works (as did the <hi>Jews</hi>) or thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of the loving kindneſs of God; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is due but reproach and confuſion. For as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is everlasting life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Can life and death then be called a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence or reward?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, life in reference to the promiſe, death in reſpect of ſin may be ſo called. For reward beareth an indifferent ſignification, and is appliable in good and bad things, to good and bad men. Of bad men and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boaſters, the Lord ſaith, <hi>They have received their reward.</hi> And this is the ſame which the good man of the houſe ſaith, <hi>Take what is thine, and be gone. Peter</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>That the wicked find the reward of their unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:62319:45"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I now plainly perceive that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which you raiſed from that Parable in our morning diſcourſe, is properly to be underſtood of the calling of the <hi>Jews;</hi> if you pleaſe therefore purſue your purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>My purpoſe was to declare the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit power of God, by which we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of the largeneſs of his Church and Kingdom. For if the Majeſty of a King is beſt conſpicuous in the abundance of rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, in the multitude of people, and a great number of Kingdoms, Provinces and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we muſt neceſſarily conclude, That the Kingdom of God, who onely can be truely ſaid to be powerful, great, and wonderful, is much bigger than that tyranny of the devil. For I will never call that Prince great, who hath a great multitude of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but I will term him powerful, to whom many pay ſubjection; and in this I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>Solomon</hi> on my ſide; <hi>In the multitude of the people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the Kings honour, but in the ſcarcity of men is the deſtruction of a Prince.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>This cannot be denyed, when thoſe things are abſtracted from perſons and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmes: but when I conſider them more near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and look upon them in the lives and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of men, I confeſs I am puzled what to think, for do you not ſee that Satan doth poſſeſs the greateſt part of the world,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62319:45"/> which as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>is covered with evil:</hi> therefore not without cauſe is the devil cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Prince of this world, and lord thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What my CAELIUS? Know you not that <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Judge not according to appearance, but judge righteous judgement?</hi> do you forget what you confeſs in the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of your Belief, when you ſay, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> which is the Communion of Saints; which had it been ſubjected to ſenſe, had not been put into our Confeſſion, which conſiſteth ſimply and abſolutely of the objects of our Faith. Let it not therefore move thee that this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, this Commonwealth of the Saints is not viſible to the eye; for it is better believed and comprehended in the mind, than diſcerned by the ſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſeeing it conſiſts of men, what is the reaſon it ſhould be inviſible?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe God in the adminiſtration of his Kingdom, differeth from the conduct of humane reaſon, or the Methods of that old beguiler. And here now we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the wonderful and admirable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. The devil filleth all place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with ſin, death, and deſolation: God diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all things in juſtice, life and healthfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſalvation. Now obſerve with what inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible art God doth this to deceive tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deceiver. Under ſin he covereth juſtice, un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62319:46"/> death life, under condemnation ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, under infirmitie ſtrength, under folly wiſdom. From hence it is ſaid that all the World is overſpread with evil: from hence Satan is ſaid to be the Prince of this world, becauſe he ſeemeth to govern all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own ſenſualitie as though there were no providence, but it is not ſo, by no means ſo; the true and legitimate Prince is he to whom the Father ſaid, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Ask of me, and I will give thee the nations for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi> He is the true Lord who conquering death, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of death ſaith in the 28 of <hi>Matth. All power is given to me both in heaven and in earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>You have proved theſe things very fully, and the matter is ſtrengthened by the nature and definition of faith, for faith is defined by the Divines to be a firm com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of thoſe things in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which are not ſeen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I rejoyce that you have ſo well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by our diſcourſe, that you can aſſiſt the cauſe I maintain. But to make it yet more clear unto you I will propound a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: We are in this life as in a Citie, which of right belongeth to ſome good Prince: but this Citie is uſurped and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a certain Tyrant with ſevere
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62319:46"/> bondage: as for example <hi>Pharaoh</hi> oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in that memorable calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: now if any man enter this Citie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Cuſtoms of it, he will ſay it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers very little from that of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which with outward appearance and ſeeming wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs followeth and obeyeth the Tyrant, but inwardly conſenteth with the true and lawful Lord: and although they can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute nothing elſe, yet they ſigh and wiſh for him, expect him, and bewail the burthen of their ſervitude: and when he ſhall come with power to chaſe and ſubdue the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to reſtore the Citie to freedom, then the Tyrant ſhall feel of what force the Faith and Love of this people is to their Lawful and merciful Prince, for in ſtead of many Subjects, he ſhall then find many Enemies, for that old ſaying is a true one; <hi>He that hath many ſervants hath many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> What? are we not all Subject and mancipated to ſin even againſt our wills? Fitly therefore may we ſay with <hi>Paul, With the mind I ſerve the Law of God, but with my body I am Subject to the dominion of ſin.</hi> Add alſo, that many men commit many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours through ignorance, and thoſe will admit excuſe and pardon, for a difference muſt be put between ſins of weakneſs, and ſins of malice and preſumption. But wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our King Chriſt Jeſus accompanied with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62319:47"/> might and Majeſty ſhall come to ſight the laſt battel with the Devil, then that infinite multitude of the Elect, that innumerable company of celeſtial Citizens ſhall appear. Now they are not diſcernable, becauſe as (I have ſaid) either through force or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance they are compelled to wear the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants colours. In the mean time, till the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of that time be ſatisfied, our pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and abundantly wiſe Prince hath ſome ſecret and clandeſtine conferences with them, heartens them and comforts them, and bids them continue faithful to him, and he will accept this their deſire of him, this Faith for perfect obedience. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he can deliver us, he delayeth it, ſuffers us to undergo the Diſcipline of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to kindle in us a greater deſire of his coming. Theſe are the Divine ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, the royal arts, which do deceive both the narrow judgement of men, and alſo elude the deceits and ſnares of the Devil; for who would ſay that in ſo many ſins there ſhould be any righteouſneſs? in ſuch a perturbation, ſuch a trifluctuation of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries any quiet reſt or peace? in ſo much folly any wiſdom? in ſo much ſervitude any liberty? or in ſo many dangers any ſafety? who would ever have thought the thief (who was even buried alive in all wickedneſs, and brought to be crucified
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62319:47"/> for his notorious and flagitious offences) had been one of the Sons of God, and of the number of the Elect? On the other ſide, who would have imagined that <hi>Judas Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> choſen to the Honour of an Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and daily and hourly a continual hearer of Divine truth, and heavenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhould not have been a Citizen of Heaven: O the depth of the riches of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable are his judgements and his waies paſt finding out? Here is the new Art, here are new reaſons of heavenly adminiſtration; this is the myſterious way of God alone, who onely is wiſe, powerful and good. <hi>Great is our Lord and of great power his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is infinite.</hi> Pſal. 147.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>By this way of judging according to the ſhallow judgement of man, I ſuppoſe <hi>Elias</hi> was deceived, when he made his complaint that he onely was left of all thoſe that did worſhip God: but what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the oracle of God to him? <hi>I have reſerved to my ſelf ſeven thouſand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal.</hi> Rom. 11.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>You gues right; and if in one place in one nation, there were ſo many (althoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to a definite number be here put for an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finite multitude) and thoſe unknown to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> greater Prophet, how many may we ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe then to have been, and now to be, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the whole World?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:62319:48"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Verily I think an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us then believe that this our heavenly King, is able and knoweth how to purchaſe to himſelf a greater kingdom, than the Enemy who hath neither wiſdom nor power.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>But upon what reaſon do you refuſe the aſcription of wiſdom and power to the Enemy, when it ſeems repugnant to his name to deny him thoſe attributes? for you may call to mind they were termed <hi>Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> or evil Spirits, from their great power or wiſdom by many of the Ancients, for <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> who followed <hi>Heſiod</hi> and other Poets, doth conceive them to be called <hi>Daemones quaſi Daimones,</hi> which ſignifieth prudent or intelligent.</p>
                  <p>I am not ignorant, that ſome of the <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> have derived the word from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is to terrifie or make afraid, becauſe ſtrength armed with malice is a terrible thing. But as concerning their power, their opinion who derive the word from the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> liketh me beſt, for there are many Greek words deduced from the Hebrew tongue. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> term both Gods and Devils <hi>Schadaim</hi> and the more ancient Graecians leaving out the firſt conſonant of the word, and reading without prickt-vowels, made it <hi>Daim,</hi> then <hi>Daimones,</hi> for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62319:48"/> both the <hi>Graecians</hi> and the <hi>Latines</hi> of elder times pronounced their dipthongues with diſtinct vowels and not confuſedly as we uſe to do, now this word ſignifieth ſtrength, fortitude, and power. And albeit <hi>Schada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> be one of the names of our omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God, yet as <hi>Elohim</hi> the proper appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the mighty Lord, is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to great Princes and Potentates, ſo the word <hi>Schadaim</hi> is promiſcuouſly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to Spirits good and bad, for although there be but one omnipotent Lord God, yet <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the Devils <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is the worldly Princes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>You have diſcourſed <hi>Caelius,</hi> very learnedly of the appellation of the word, neither will I labour to urge any thing in contradiction of it; for it ſtrongly argueth their power in that they are of a ſenſible and an indefatigable nature: beſides the uſe and experience of infinite buſineſs and occurrences, muſt needs inſtruct them with an unſpeakable knowledge; for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and length of dayes joined with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, muſt needs bring forth incredible effects, but as there are two ſorts of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom one Heavenly and Holy, another that <hi>deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, Deviliſh, James</hi> the 3. ſo likewiſe there are two ſorts of power. For as the laſt is not properly fortitude but boldneſs,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62319:49"/> not power but impotence, and violence; ſo that is not ſtrictly and truly to be termed wiſdom, but malice; that is a crafty and deceitful ſubtilety to work miſchief: for as upon an approch of danger, if the mind be egged on by its own concupiſcence and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular deſires, and not by conſideration of the publick good, this attempt is rather a vitious audacity than a warrantable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: ſo knowledge without charity, and prudence without Juſtice, is malice and ſubdolous fraudulencie (as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith) not wiſdom. Therefore when the all power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wiſdom of God doth fruſtrate and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate the wiles of Satan, tis an impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie to ſay that the wiſdom of God hath overcome the wiſdom of the Devil; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that his malice is ſubdued by wiſdom. Alſo when we ſpeak of the power of the Enemy, we ſhould ſay, that audacitie is quelled by valour, ſury is vanquiſhed by fortitude, and raſhneſs diſappointed by counſel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing can be more truly ſpoken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Having therefore ſpoken of the power and wiſdom of our omnipotent God, how ſhall we ſpeak of the goodneſs, mercy and clemency of our moſt indulgent and long ſuffering Father? So incomprehenſible i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his mercy, that like an exuberant river, nay a boundles Ocean, it diffuſeth it ſelf and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62319:49"/> refreſheth all the corners of the earth. Here I am ſtruck dumb, and aſtoniſhed at the wonderful plenty of conſiderations that roul and flow in upon me; ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and we find him not ſo wealthy in any thing as in mercy; he chiefly delights himſelf in the publication, the iteration, the exaltation of his mercy; he diſcloſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, expreſſeth himſelf, manifeſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and communicateth himſelf in mercy. <hi>David</hi> ſaith Pſalm 33. <hi>The earth is full of the goodneſs of the Lord,</hi> and in another place, <hi>the Lord is endued with plentiful mercy, and under the ſhadow of his wings all people have ſafety.</hi> If I reckon up the teſtimonies of the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, I find not a word in them but magnifieth the mercy of our God? Let <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak for the reſt who himſelf found ſo great mercy. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>And you hath he quickned who were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, wherein in time paſt ye walked according to the courſs of this world, according to the power of the Prince of the air, the Spirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience: among whom we alſo had our converſation in times paſt in the luſts of our fleſh, fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, even as others: but God who is rich in mercy, for his great love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loved us, even when we were dead
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62319:50"/> in ſins hath quickned us together with Chriſt (by grace ye are ſaved) and hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places in Chriſt Jeſus: that in the ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace, in his kindneſs towards us in Chriſt Jeſus: for by grace are ye ſaved, through ſaith and that not of your ſelves: it is the gift of God: not of works leaſt any man ſhould boaſt. For we are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore orda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ned that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> Here we may behold, with what magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of expreſſion the Apoſtle doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge, and depredicate the goodneſs and mercy of God, and how we muſt diſclaime and abandon all our own works and merits, by a ſtedfaſt adheſion unto, and a ſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the eternal Love of God unto us in Chriſt Jeſus. But how is God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous over all the world for his mercy, and eminent for the riches of his goodnes in the ſalvation of a few, and the damnation of the reſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Wonderful things I confeſs are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto us of the mercy of God in the Holy Scriptures: yet ſome men are not backward to ſay, that his mercy is as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in the Salvation of one individual Soul, as in the preſervation of a thouſand millions: becauſe to that Soul which the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62319:50"/> mercy of God hath delivered from death eternal, there was due an infinite puniſhment for infinite tranſgreſſions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are the inventions and vain imaginations of men, which are too much accuſtomed to meaſure things Divine by the rule of humane judgement. Suppoſe there were in this Citie ſome man exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wealthy, and abounding with all kind of outward bleſſings: ſuppoſe, I ſay, that he ſhould ſhare his munificence to ſome few, nay beſtow all his wealth upon them, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving abundance of other Citizens in an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, wanting, and contemptible condition; would you think this man as truely liberal, as if he had made an equal diſtribution of all his eſtate among all the Citizens?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>By no means, but extreamly cruel, and a homicide, for <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid very truely, <hi>He that ſeeth a man in miſerie, is able to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour him, and refuſeth, that man ſlayeth and murthereth him.</hi> But to ſay ſo of God were horrid impiety, becauſe it is Lawfull for him to do what pleaſeth him, for his will is the perfect reaſon of his works.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>But doe you not remember the old ſaying, that good is of a communicable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that the more it is ſpread and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſtill the more good it is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I have often heard it, and alwayes took it for a rag of Philoſophy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:62319:51"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh brother <hi>Caelius</hi> it is Divine; for good and true are convertible terms, and of whomſoever predicated whether of <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Cicero, Paul</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> yet they flow from God whoſe nature and eſſence is good and true, and becauſe as you ſaid, whatſoever he willeth is good and juſt: and that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him to be called rich in mercy, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this muſt appear in the glorious ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of many men: otherwiſe why doth <hi>David</hi> ſing out, <hi>the earth is full of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God;</hi> and why is he called <hi>the Father of mercies and the God of all conſolation?</hi> O the blind envy of ſome men that would abridge, contract and engroſs this goodneſs to ſome few pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſons! O the ingratitude of others that indeavour to traduce and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate the benignity of God, as if he were ſome Tyrant or mercileſs deſtroyer! Some perhaps are ſtill diffident and require an indubitable ſign that may remove and baniſh all heſitation, behold the greateſt pledge, the firmeſt ſecurity, even Chriſt Jeſus the ſon of God, upon whoſe coming God ſet ſorth a Declaration of his Love, <hi>for him hath he ſent into the world, and upon him hath he cast the burthen of all our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Iſaiah</hi> the 53. and again, <hi>behold the Lord ſhall give you a ſign, a Virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bear a Son, and his name ſhall be called Emanuel.</hi> This is that ſign which we
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62319:51"/> read of in the 12. of <hi>Matthew, An evil and an adulterous g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neration ſeeketh a ſign, but no ſign ſhall be given them, ſave onely that of the Prophet Jonas,</hi> to wit, <hi>the death of Chriſt, and his riſing again the third day.</hi> What greater ſignificancy of love could the Lord exhibit to miſerable mankind, than to ſend his Son, his onely Son, to be the reconciliation for our tranſgreſſions? or who now can ſcruple the amplitude, the immenſity of this goodneſs, this Love, this mercy? how ſhall we be able with the Saints to know and comprehend the height, the depth, the length, the breadth of this mercy? it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie that the Love of Chriſt be the greateſt of all other, not onely in reſpect of the magnitude, but alſo the multitude of ſinners, otherwiſe we ſhould diſrobe and denudate it of its proper dimenſions, and who now will be ſo raſhly bold to ſay, that the benefit of ſo much love, and ſo great goodneſs, ſhould be confined to a paucity of men? for my part, I think no man can harbour ſuch a thought without a guilt of ſacriledge: what? did he not deliver the greater part of the world from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes, when he prayed unto his Father upon the Croſs to forgive thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> and Aliens which were the complotters and contrivers of his death? <hi>Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>forgive them for they know not what they do;</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:62319:52"/> and he ſaid rightly they know not what they doe; <hi>for had they known</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul they had never crucified the Lord of life.</hi> 1. Cor. 2. Now if Princes, Magiſtrates, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as <hi>Peter</hi> witneſſeth in the 3. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> killed him through imprudence; what ſhall we think of all the world beſide? of them that had, and have at this day juſt cauſes of invincible ignorance? Shall we exclude all theſe from the kingdom of God? We cannot certainly if we diligently contemplate the nature and goodneſs of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if we think upon the clemency of our Lord Chriſt, and what he required of us: for he prayeth for all them that ſinned through imprudence and infirmity. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he pray in vain. Paul who at firſt was a perſecutour and a contumelious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſaith, <hi>Notwithſtanding that he obtained mercy becauſe he did it ignorantly, in unbelief.</hi> And then he addeth, <hi>This is a faithfull ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worthie of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of which I am Chief. Howbeit, for this cauſe I obtained mercy, that to me firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuffering, for a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to them which ſhould hereafter believe on him to life everlaſting.</hi> And did not God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate this before to <hi>Jonas?</hi> Who was grieved that he would ſpare <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and deſtroy his Gourd that did ſhed him from
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62319:52"/> the violence of the heat: therefore God ſaith unto him, <hi>And haſt thou pitty on the Gourd, for which thou haſt not laboured, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther madeſt it grow, which ſprang up in one night, and periſhed in one night: and ſhould not I ſpare</hi> Nineveh <hi>that great City, wherein are more than ſixſcore thouſand perſons tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cannot diſcern between their right hand and their left hand, and alſo much cattel?</hi> Here we plainly ſee the moſt benign and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God doth ſpare a multitude, and avert the preſent puniſhment of his ſeverity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their ignorance. And ſhall we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he, who remitteth a temporal judgement, becauſe of unadviſed actions, and involuntary ſins, will inflict an eternal mulct? or that he judgeth the death of the body, to be greater than the deſtruction of the ſoul? Ignorance doubtleſs hath ſome excuſe, eſpecially if it be not tainted with fraud or malice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>This indeed is not denied, yet they ſay that Chriſt died indeed for all meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but, for a few onely effectually: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe few onely do expect that advantage and benefit of Salvation by his death, and very few are found worthy of that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable treaſure of his ſatisfaction. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is not blame-worthy, who offered himſelf liberally for all men, but they are to be condemned, who refuſed this propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:62319:53"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh how many errours are contained in thoſe few words! for as <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>curus,</hi> that he might not offend the <hi>Athenians,</hi> outwardly acknowledged a God, but in judgement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him; ſo theſe men in words confeſs the death of Chriſt, but deny the power of it. For when the <hi>Epicureans</hi> durſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Gods, yet they denied a Providence which is inſeparably conjoyned to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, and ſo by conſequence they denied God, but more modeſtly and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertly: and are not theſe men guilty of the ſame prevarication? They teach that Chriſt died for all men, and affirm at the ſame time that the benefit of his death doth concern very few men: What is this but to deny the virtue of his paſſion, the glory of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience? to ſay that men can aboliſh the energy, force, and effect of his divine love? S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith far otherwiſe, when with ſo much gravity and mellifluous plenty, he doth aver that <hi>no force is able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which he hath manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted unto us in Chriſt Jeſus. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? it is God that juſtifieth; who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for us. Who ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> then ſeparate us from the love in Chriſt?</hi> Rom. 8. Me thinks they that are ſo perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62319:53"/> in the defence of that Opinion that Chriſts bloud was ſprinkled only upon a few, do much reſemble that man who made a moſt magnificent feaſt, fit in the preparation of it to entertain a whole City, but when the gueſts came to ſit down that were invited, there appeared onely a very thin number, and might not a man demand, wherefore all this preparation? mountains are delivered of a mouſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Who will deny this? for to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould he prepare many things with oſtentation, which he did not intend to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>But far otherwiſe doth our Lord deal by us, for when ſome had refuſed to come to his Supper, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. <hi>Go out,</hi> ſaith he (to a ſervant) <hi>into the ſtreets and lanes of the city, and bring in hither the poor, and the lame, the maimed, the halt, and the blind, and when this was done, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t room was remaining, Go</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>into the high-ways and hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and compel them to come in, that my houſe may be full.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh the wonderful benignity of the Lord! to whom it ſeemeth not enough to invite onely, but to compel men to a frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his plenty. But how doth he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel men? for this phraſe may ſound harſh to ſome ears, eſpecially ſeeing our Lord ſeemeth to be of a different Opinion, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62319:54"/> 
                     <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and is taken by violence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, we may call them violent, who deny themſelves in the brideling of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and moderating their ſenſualities, who oppoſe the activity of Faith againſt the wit of reaſon, and prefer the Kingdom of God, before all the fugitive pleaſures of all the kingdoms of this world. <hi>He that will follow me,</hi> ſaith the King himſelf, <hi>let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf,</hi> (this is that holy violence) <hi>Let him take up his croſs and follow me. For the Kingdom of God is not overcome by any man, but by him who hath firſt overcome himſelf.</hi> He that obtains this conqueſt, as <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith, is <hi>Victor victorum,</hi> Conquerour of conquerours; Again God is then ſaid to compel, when of chips of Hell, he makes Cedars of Paradiſe, <hi>Of ſons of wrath, ſons of God, and coheirs with Chriſt:</hi> when by a kiſs of love, and a ſpiritual embrace, he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth them up to Heaven, who by nature were concenterd in hell. Thus when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> did precipitate hlmſelf into blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and did exagitate the world with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, God ſuddenly wraps him up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third Heaven. This bleſſed compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alſo did they undergo, that were of the Baptiſts Auditory, who as ſoon as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was at an end, contended in a holy faith, who ſhould firſt lay hold on Chriſt;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62319:54"/> for our Lord meant nothing elſe in thoſe words, but to expreſs the vehemency of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in the multitude, to attain everlaſting happineſs. This he alſo ſhewed in the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a conquered city, into which the Souldiers ſtrive to enter. Of which matter, if any man doubt, let him read the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke,</hi> in the ſeventh chapter, who expounding thoſe things which Chriſt ſaid of <hi>John,</hi> and of the Kingdom of God, ſaith, <hi>All the people that heard him, and the Publicanes juſtified God, being baptized with the baptiſm of John.</hi> Now God dealeth with us, even as we uſe to do with tender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, we hang up a piece of money, or ſome other thing, and ſhew it the child; pointing to it, as a reward of his weak en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to reach it, we invite and allure him to take it, which when he cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, then by little and little we let down the money neerer the childs hands, till he have caught it. Then we rejoyce, the child triumpheth that he hath got the gold, and we ſhout, and praiſe the child, as if he had done ſome great matter. But tell me now, what did this little infant perform? You placed the money, you provoked him to take it, you let it down that he might reach it, onely you did not put the money into his hands, and yet you praiſed him and coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered him, as if he alone had done all. But
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62319:55"/> God, beſides all theſe things, doth more for us. He doth not onely ſet a felicity before us, invite us, excite us, and raiſe us up, but alſo by the gracious inſtinct of his Spirit, ſweetly allure us, and compel us to like it, to will it, to chooſe it, to embrace it, and to love it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>O bleſſed conſtraint, O delightful vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence! let us therefore with them congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate this priviledge, that he hath adopt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to the participation of the glorious inheritance of the Saints, that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued us from the powers of darkneſs, and tranſlated us to the Kingdom of his deareſt Son.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>We ought indeed to return our thanks to him, but who can offer thanks worthy of ſo great mercies? Our moſt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prince will fill his houſe, will people his Kingdom; but how large can we ſuppoſe this houſe, this Kingdom to be, when it is as capacious as his love, as far extended as his goodneſs, and as patulous as his mercy, in which there is ſound neither meaſure nor circumſcription. And becauſe this houſe is capable to entertain a multitude of gueſts, and not a paucity onely, therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In my Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs houſe are many manſions, John</hi> 14. Now compare the words of our Saviour, with the opinion of theſe men; they ſay, His houſe is a narrow houſe, a ſmall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62319:55"/> houſe, and that it ſhall alſo continue above half empty; the Lord witneſſeth his deſire to have it filled, and as <hi>Iſaia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſaith, <hi>It ſhall be even too na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>row by reaſon of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants,</hi> chap. 49. Now conſider, who is moſt worthy of belief, God or man, that is, truth or a lie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Who will make any doubt of that, when <hi>God onely is true, and all men are lyars?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What then hath our King omitted, wherein hath he been deficient in goodneſs or wiſdom, that his Kingdom ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, amplified, and repleniſhed? <hi>Moſes</hi> the Commander of the <hi>Iſra lites,</hi> by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of God, appointed them ſix Cities for Refuge, three on this ſide, and three on the further ſide of the River of <hi>Jordan,</hi> that they who killed a man unawares through errour, might flee thither and eſcape. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus,</hi> the firſt Founder of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſet up a Sanctuary alſo, unto which any malefactour might flee, and by that means avoid puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: This was the firſt beginning and foundation of that ſtupendious Empire of the <hi>Romanes;</hi> neither is it worth a wonder, for who is not moved with the names of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and freedom, and ſafety? who doth not chearfully run thither to find it where it is promiſed? the ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> conſecrated every fiftieth year to liberty and plenty, for in that year the ſlaves were emancipated,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62319:56"/> and the bond-men made free: New tables were inſtituted, new Ordinances deviſed, and poſſeſſions did revert to the owners, by their former right to the inheritance: the Harveſt and the Vintage of that year, was in common; it was proclaimed by the ſound of Rams-horns and Trumpets, and from thence called the year of <hi>Jubilee.</hi> But hath the wiſdom and goodneſs of God been leſs liberal to us? hath he not ſent Chriſt, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did not he himſelf in Chriſt the Lord, come to conſtitute this Sanctuary, to reveal this Tower of liberty, ſafety, and refuge? And with what reaſon, and upon what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions he did it, will eaſily be underſtood: for they that haſtened to thoſe Sanctuaries, fled thither with body and goods, and were oftentimes taken or killed, before they eſcaped thither; But to this Refuge of our Salvation, it is enough to run with faith and unfeigned deſires. Their Sanctuaries were limited to a certain place, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of years; but to this there may at any time, be a confluence of any people, from any part of the world. Their places of refuge were not capable of all men, and were appointed almoſt but for one Nation: this Heavenly Tower of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence will receive an infinit multitude of people, and is common to all men. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy onely and the goods were there preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62319:56"/> here man is inveſted with glorious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and enfeaffed with eternal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Few were there made better, but if they came thither wicked, wicked they there continued: Here upon our firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, we are transſubſtantiated into new creatures, and throughly changed, as if we were new born again, for our gracious King, who hath opened unto us this Sanctuary of Salvation, doth not onely remit unto us the puniſhment due to our tranſgreſſions, but doth alſo make us juſt, holy, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Laſtly, they who fled to the places of Succour, appointed by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Romulus,</hi> changed their Lord, and were free from all paſt dangers, but afterwards they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed, if they were found guilty of new delinquency; nor after that relapſe was there any Refuge allowed them: But in our Sanctuary, as often as a man offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſo often is he pardoned, provided that with true repentance he maketh his appeal, and preferreth his petition to the King. And he that runneth to this Holy Aſylum, this Heavenly Temple, is no longer a ſervant, but for ever free, being manumitted by the ſon of God. For ſuch is the goodneſs of our King, that he will make us all the ſons of God, and coheirs with his Son, Prieſts, Prophets, and partakers of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:62319:57"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>But what and where is this <hi>Aſylum,</hi> this City of Refuge, and year of Salvation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This <hi>Caelius,</hi> is the <hi>Church</hi> of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the City of the Saints, the Pillar and Prop of truth: and this year of <hi>Jubilee</hi> is all that intervention of time, from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of Chriſt, to the Day of Judgement: of which time the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Now the acceptable time approacheth, the Day of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation draweth neer.</hi> This is not more at this time, than at another, not more in this year, than in another, not more in <hi>Europe,</hi> than in <hi>Aſia</hi> or <hi>Africa,</hi> not more at <hi>London,</hi> than at <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore is the Church ſtiled the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> For ſeeing this great City conſiſteth of ſuch men as believe in, and reverence the living God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are diſperſed, there is the Church, and the year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> and that ſempiternal place of Refuge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your opinion of thoſe that never heard of theſe things? or if they have heard of them, it was onely by a ſcattered report, but they had not the inſinuations of them, by the preaching of the Goſpel, or any Divine Inſtitutions? For it is certain, that many Nations (as we have lately had experience by the diſcoveries in <hi>America</hi>) have lived and died, who never heard of Chriſt. But to think that all thoſe men for ſo many ages, were predetermined to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62319:57"/> is not conſentaneous to the Divine goodneſs, and juſt government of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King. Although it may appear a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult matter to conclude either way of their final condition, yet I conceive no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of them, then thoſe who lived before the coming of Chriſt, and the promulgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for if they did, or now do obſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he law of nature, worſhip our God, do nothing to others that they would not have done to themſelves, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them of ſuch evil doings, my opinion is they may be ſaved, for they that feared God, were always dear and acceptable to him, as <hi>Peter</hi> witneſſeth in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> ſuch were <hi>Abimelech, Melchiſedech, Jethro, Joh,</hi> and his four friends: <hi>Hiram</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the King of the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Sheba, Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the Wiſe men at the Nativity of Chriſt, with innumerable others (as it is highly probable) un-mentioned in the Book of God. For this was the judgement of the moſt Ancient Fathers <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> as it is recorded in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, <hi>Qui verbum non accepit auditione,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Clemens) ei vema dandi propter igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiam.</hi> Who hath not heard the Word preached, his ignorance ſhall excuſe him; for as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>How ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y believe in him, of whom they have not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62319:58"/> heard?</hi> The untaught ſhall not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but they who have heard the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Chriſt, and deſpiſe the offers of his grace. This is the peremptory Sanction of our Lord himſelf, <hi>Go</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>preach the Goſpel, and teach all Nations, he that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> This is the Law and moſt juſt Decree of our King: that as he who heareth the Goſpel and believeth, ſhall be ſaved, ſo he that heareth and believeth not, ſhall be damned. From whence it follows, that he is not condemned by the Goſpel, who hath not heard the Goſpel; but they are therefore ſeperated to condemnation, becauſe they contemned the law of nature, and the teſtimony of conſcience, by which they ſhall be judged, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth in the ſecond to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> this is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal purport of all Laws, that they to whom a law is given, ſhall, if they tranſgreſs that law, be judged by it, but not thoſe who are not bound by that law. And if this be obſerved in all well-governed Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, which are as images of that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom, much more may we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that it is obſerved by God himſelf, who is King of kings, and the common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all mankind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed theſe things ſeem moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our righteous God, and altogether
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62319:58"/> agreeable to his gentle nature: thus we ſee, he would not inflict puniſhments upon the <hi>Ninivites</hi> without cauſe declared, for he firſt ſent his Prophet to them, that by his preaching they might underſtand the will of God. Yet that ſaying of <hi>Peter</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> doth ſeem to thwart this opinion, for he teacheth, <hi>That there is no other name under heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved, but the name of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Acts. 4.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not otherwiſe to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, than (as we ſaid before) to concern them to whom that name hath been preached: although whoſoever is ſaved, hath ſalvation by God his Saviour, as he proclaimeth of himſelf in <hi>Iſaiah, I, even I am the Lord, and beſides me there is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> But that is Jeſus Chriſt, God to be praiſed for ever; although explicitly and declaratively he hath not been revealed to them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs I thought thus within my ſelf, but I was willing to hear your opinion, but when you ſaid a little before, ſpeaking of the Church, that it was whereſoever men did believe, or ſhould believe; wherefore made you that addition, ſhould believe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe at all times, and in all ages, many are elected to this kingdom, which are not yet called, not compelled by faith
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62319:59"/> to enter, as were <hi>Saul, Cornelius</hi> the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, and <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> the Proconſul, and innumerable others whoſe vocation and ingreſs was by the Lord, for ſome time deſerred; who becauſe they were from all eternity appointed to this kingdom, are therefore all Citizens and Members of this heavenly Common-wealth: this is manifeſt by theſe and others, who the goodneſs of God being revealed, are afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into this kingdom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>They ſay that <hi>Cornelius</hi> oponed a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into this kingdom by his prayers and Alms-deeds, and this they confirm by thoſe words of the Angel to him, <hi>Thy prayers and thy Almes are come up for a memorial before God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The abettors of ſuch fancies are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious to God, and ignorant of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; they reproch God, for they rob him of his Honour, and give the glory to man; &amp; they are ignorant of the Scriptures, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning an open truth. Their errour ariſeth partly from a non-conſideration of the words preceding and ſubſequent, which if they had perpended, they had never daſhed againſt this Rock. What hath S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the beginning of this Chapter? That <hi>Cornelius</hi> was a devour man, and one that feared God, with all his houſe, which gave much Almes to the people, and prayed to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62319:59"/> God alway. Afterwards thoſe men that were ſent by <hi>Cornelius</hi> give him this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, that he was <hi>a juſt man, feared God, and of good report among all the nation of the Jews.</hi> Who now doth not plainly ſee that his piety to, and his fear of God are firſt commended: then his Almes and good deeds are ſpoken of? he was a Religious and a good man, and therefore gave many Almes to the poor, and prayed to God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which were the fruits and effects of his piety. Therefore it is ſaid, he was of good report among the <hi>Jews.</hi> But from whence came theſe good effects? Not from his good deeds; for the tree muſt be good before the fruit can be good, as our Lord ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. For the cauſe cannot follow the effect any more than a daughter can bring forth her Mother. But who made him Religious and juſt, and fearing God? Who but he, that circumciſeth the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkins of our hearts? That taketh away our ſtony hearts, and giveth us hearts of fleſh, and new Spirits? <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11. He, I ſay, made <hi>Cornelius</hi> both Religious and devout: and were not theſe things declared unto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> by the Divine oracle of God: for when he ſuppoſed that all the reſt of the Nations were alienated from the benefit of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, the Angel telleth him, <hi>Thoſe things which God hath purified, call not thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62319:60"/> Acts</hi> 10. Here God witneſſeth that he had purged, prepared, and conſecrated <hi>Cornelius</hi> to himſelf. And although it was ſpoken becauſe of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> yet the words concern all thoſe that God hath choſen and adorned with the beautiful knowledge of the Goſpel. And whereas it is ſaid that his prayers, and giving of Almes went up to God as a memorial, nothing more is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but that God heareth the prayers of the Godly, that their good works are acceptable to him, and that he hath them in remembrance, as flowing from himſelf the Fountain of all good gifts. And where it is ſaid, that he was frequent in prayer, it is evident that this proceeded from a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſpiration. For as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, but the Spirit it ſelf maketh interceſſion for us with unutterable groans. Rom.</hi> 8. Now if he was endued with the Spirit of God, as certainly he was, and that his Almes-deeds and his prayers were accepted, it is as certain that he had ſaith, <hi>without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> doth moſt plainly teach. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. And if he had the illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Faith, then his heart was purified and cleanſed, as <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifieth of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> and other Gentiles in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That God had enlightened them by his Holy Spirit, and purged their minds by Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:62319:60"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceive that by degrees you have come to the right explication of the truth; but there is yet one thing to be enucleated, for <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Of a truth I now perceive, that God is no reſpecter of perſons: but in every nation, he that feareth him and worketh righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, is accepted by him. Act.</hi> 10. Here he ſheweth that by good works a man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſpeech of the Apoſtle, meaneth nothing elſe, but what diverſe other holy ſentences do teach, that God in his election of, and his Love to mankind, hath regard onely to their goodneſs and glorie, not to their original, their pedigree, their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, their ſex, their age, their merit, or any other perſonal attributes. This truth is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified in the perſon of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> whom God called being an alien, and dignified him with a place in his kingdom. The ſigns of Election are an ingenuous and a reverential fear of God, like to that of obedient children towards their parents, from whence there ariſeth in them, a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and a ſtedfaſt perſwaſion of the love of God to them, and from thence again groweth a delight in the Law of God, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency in the works of righteouſneſs, he that is accepted by God, he feareth, he honoureth, loveth, and truſteth in God: for it behoveth that the perſon of that man
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62319:61"/> be gracious and acceptable, whoſe duties or offices of Love are accepted: for no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances are acceptable from him, againſt whom we entertain a prejudice or aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, of this we have experience in the common civilities of life, but with God there is no prejudice, for he is the ſearcher of the heart. And <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever doth work righteouſneſs, is born of God.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, he is born of God,</hi> that is, therefore ſome men live juſtly, ſome man believeth Jeſus to be the Chriſt, becauſe he is juſtified by God, and endued with holineſs and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs by him: for unleſs he thus be born of God, he is unable to perform any thing juſtly and rightly, or to believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt. This the Lord himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth upon <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion, that he was <hi>the Son of the Immortal God. Verily</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>fleſh and bloud hath not reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this unto thee, but my Father, which is in Heaven.</hi> Now there is this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Divine and humane juſtice, he that is not juſtified by God, may execute hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane juſtice, for fear of puniſhment, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of glorie, or hope of other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; but no man is exerciſed in heavenly juſtice, who is not firſt juſtified, purged by Faith, and aſſiſted with grace. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no wonder, that whoſoever feareth
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62319:61"/> God, and worketh righteouſneſs, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God; becauſe <hi>the fear of God is the beginning of wiſdom, and a good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have all they that keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> With this fear, as with ſalt, the Lord doth ſeaſon their hearts, and preſerve from corruption (even whileſt they are ignorant of him) thoſe that he purpoſeth to call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his kingdom. This inchoation of their liberty, is afterwards perfected in the time of their vocation, by the preaching of the Goſpel and by Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I have received full ſatisfaction, and I hope hereafter that both my ſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will give greater credit to the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, then to the perverſe opinions and interpretations of men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Now that we may conclude this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, I ſay that whereſoever, or when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſuch are found, in that moment of time they have attained to this Sanctuary, this propitious year of Jubilee. Onely as it is written, <hi>Let us call upon the name of the Lord, and we ſhall not be diſappointed.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call upon the name of the Lord, ſhall eſcape. Joel.</hi> 2. Alſo, <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous flyeth unto it, and is ſafe. Prov.</hi> 18. To this tower, this ſanctuary, the Lord himſelf beckneth the poor, the miſerable, the wretched, the deſperate ſinners, in this ſweet invitation,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62319:62"/> 
                     <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> Theſe are the wayes, the ſecrets of holy ſtate, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Policies, which our King uſeth for the Inſtanration of his kingdom. And if the kingdoms of the earth are enlarged by ſuch artifice, how much more ſhall we think the kingdom of Heaven to be dilated, which is far more capacious, more firm, and more eaſie of acceſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I ſuppoſe it will infinitely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the kingdom, or rather the dungeon of the Devil: even as much as there are more who wiſh and deſire eaſe, impunity, Honour and Salvation, then who are in love with labours, puniſhments, ſervitude, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny, and death eternal, and certainly but few men will precipitate themſelves into theſe calamities, when they may with ſuch facility redeem themſelves from the fear of them. And although a ſmall induſtry one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeemeth neceſſarie to the prevention of theſe endles torments, yet we ſee but few men that contend to get to this refuge, this moſt pleaſant Citie; and what ſhould be the cauſe of this ſlackneſs, this dulneſs; this indiligence is to me altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The cauſe is manifeſt; Firſt that which I named before, to wit that the new reaſon of ſtate, which our King maketh uſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62319:62"/> of in the adminiſtration of his affairs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaveth thoſe that with the judgement of men, ſeek after this citie as gloriouſly viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and conſpicuous. Secondly, the Church is congregated and conſtituted out of this holy Sanctuary, by the preaching of the word, and the adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and theſe being concealed from the greater part of the World, by this means, this citie for a long time was kept hid, and ſo little taken notice of; that it was ſcarce diſcernable who were the true Citizens. But as ſoon as the glad tidings of the Goſpel have arrived, then we ſee them flock to this citie as in the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. For when Chriſt himſelf had ſaid that the kingdom of God was at hand, and after that he had exhorted men to <hi>bring forth fruit worthie of repentance;</hi> he then called them all unto him, with that joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſummons, <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you eaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of this joyful invitation, this liberal year, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold, when ſpeaking in the Perſon of Chriſt, he ſaith, <hi>I am endued with the Spirit of the Lord, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah hath Anointed me, and ſent me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare joyful tidings: to heal them of broken Spirits, and to give liberty to them that are in bondage, ſight to the blind, to deliver the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed out of their ſtreights, and to preach the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62319:63"/> joyful year of the Lord.</hi> The Apoſtles alſo, thoſe faithful Embaſſadours of Chriſt, did invite all mortal men to this great benefit, this moſt bleſſed kingdom. <hi>Old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new: and all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to himſelf in Chriſt Jeſus, and hath given to us the miniſterie of reconciliation,</hi> to wit, <hi>that God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and hath committed to us the word of reconciliation. Now then, we are embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, we pray you, in Chriſts ſtead, be ye reconciled to God: for he hath made him who knew no ſin to be ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſhortly after, falſe Apoſtles and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Embaſſadours, brought in humane traditions, and began to lay upon mens ſhoulders the burthen and heavy yoak of the Law, which things did deject, not erect mens minds, did terrifie them, not allure them, did wound them, not heal them: from whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> came to paſs that few made their approach to this kingdom, or if they drew near, they ſoon returned and departed. For the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is not propagated and advanced by the ſword, but by preaching, by the energie of the Spirit, by good example, patience, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62319:63"/> meekneſs, juſtice, temperance, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, goodneſs, faith, lenity, long-ſuffering, and all thoſe bleſſed and peaceable fruits of the true Spirit of God. So our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſo his Diſciples propagated the truth, and ſowed the Heavenly Doctrine of Chriſt in mens hearts. For our Lord as <hi>Hilarie</hi> told <hi>Conſtantinus; Auguſtus</hi> did rather teach than exact a knowledge and confeſſion of himſelf; and giving Authority to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts by the frequent atteſtation of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, he deſpiſed a will that was any other way compelled to acknowledge him. And full of truth are theſe words, for nothing ſo free as the judgement in Religion. For Religion flouriſheth by ſound reaſon and ſtrong perſwaſion, not by fear and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. It is defended &amp; preſerved by dying, not by killing; by patience, not by cruelty; by juſtice, not by butchery; by faith, not by fraud &amp; rotten policy. For he that will eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Religion by imperious ordinances &amp; force, doth not ſeek to defend it, but to violate and pollute it. But becauſe we ſee the night approaching <hi>Caelius,</hi> unleſs you have ought to interpoſe, I ſhall deſcend to ſuch places of Scripture, as ſeem to favour this my opinion, <hi>of the amplitude of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I have not the leaſt doubt remaining, and I earneſtly intreat you, before the night
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62319:64"/> prevent us, to haſten to thoſe proofs as the chief end of our meeting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>In the firſt place therefore, weigh diligently that magnificent promiſe of God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo often repeated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated. God promiſeth, and confirmeth his promiſe with an oath; that he will make his ſeed as the duſt of the earth, ſo that if a man can number the duſt of the earth, then ſhall he number the ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. And again in the 22. chapter, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, <hi>In bleſſing I will bleſs thee, and in multiplying, I will multiply thee in thy ſeed as the Stars of the Heaven, and as the ſand which is upon the Sea-ſhore, and thy ſeed ſhall poſſeſs the gate of his enemies: and in thy ſeed ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Here I would know of any man, whether God in this inimitable (as to us) and ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable promiſe, did intend that the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the <hi>Elect,</hi> (for that they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignified by the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> is plainly ſhewed in the 4. to the <hi>Romanes</hi>) ſhould be inferiour to the number of the <hi>Reprobate?</hi> Who will dare to ſay ſo, when he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſeed to thoſe things which exceed all other things for number, yea indeed, which are themſelves numberleſs? For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Archimedes,</hi> that noble Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, ſuppoſed that he could number the ſand, not onely about <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> but of all
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62319:64"/> the habitable and in-habitable parts of the world; and undertook to write a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of this ſuppoſal to <hi>Gelo,</hi> then King of <hi>Sicilie:</hi> yet the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> teacheth otherwiſe. <hi>What man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the waters in the hollow of his hand? and meted out the Heavens with a ſpan? or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the duſt of the earth in a meaſure? or weighed the mountains in ſcales, and the hills in a ballance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus compariſons of this nature have been adhibited, to demonſtrate ſuch things unto us, which in their kind admit of no compariſon. From whence it follows, that the progeny of <hi>Abraham</hi> is more numerous and copious, than all others. Moreover, all the Faithful being comprehended in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> there is in the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Holy Ghoſt, a kind of <hi>tacite</hi> contention againſt that Opinion <hi>of the Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Believers,</hi> for as often, and as much as he amplifies the Kingdom of God, ſo often, and ſo much he ſpeaks in diminution of the kingdom of darkneſs. Neither in this can I accord with S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who ſaith theſe words are uttered in an Hyperbole, yet when he labours to declare the matter, any man may perceive he is miſtaken. For in his Book <hi>Of the City of God,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>That the ſeed of</hi> Abraham <hi>is leſs in number than the multitude of the wicked.</hi> Suppoſe the ſand of the Sea-ſhore, or the duſt of the earth do much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62319:65"/> the number of the whole generation of mankind, What then? we do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the number of the Elect, is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the number of the Sands: but by the compariſon this onely is in queſtion, Whether the Holy ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> do not ſurmount the number of the wicked? but if it be not implied that the number of the Elect is the greater, why ſhould it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a thing that is infinit? If ſome man had come, and ſaid, That this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (ſo high that it exceeds belief) is more agreeable to the multitude of the wicked, which is much above that of the faithful, would he not hereby ſecretly inſinuate, that here was no reliſh of Divine wiſdom in this compariſon? But if to think any ſuch thing, much more to ſay it, be impious and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable, it is manifeſt, and follows undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that the multitude of ſuch as belong to the Kingdom of God, is much the greater. But to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath not God added this alſo, <hi>That in the ſeed of</hi> Abraham <hi>all Nations ſhall be bleſſed? Gal.</hi> 3. But how ſhall they all be bleſſed, if the major part be excluded from eternal happineſs? One of theſe two things is neceſſary there to be allowed, either (which I abhor to think) that God is a lyar, or elſe that the number of the bleſſed is not equiparated by any other number, and which of theſe two is to be choſen, I leave to the pious Reader to judge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:62319:65"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>You conclude ſolidly and truly; for as <hi>Fabius</hi> ſheweth, an Hyperbole is then to be known, when the matter expreſſed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth all natural meaſure. Now theſe promiſes are not vulgar, but ſo ample, ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and honourable, that the narrow minds of mortal men, ſhould be ſtruck with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration as often as they contemplate the bleſſed multitude of the glorious Saints.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſpeak the truth. But that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one who is wrapped up in a mantle of piety, hath been always buſie and diligent to eclipſe this truth. I will now produce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe I know every new argument is a freſh vexation to that fiend. In <hi>Exodus</hi> God doth wonderfully ſet forth the goodneſs of his own nature, for ſuch is his clemency, that he promiſeth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to a thouſand generations in pardoning ſins and tranſgreſſions, but threatneth ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance onely to the third or fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Conſider now what proportion there is between one thouſand and four, and know that there will be as great an inequality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the glorious free men of Jeſus Chriſt, and the few and miſerable bond-ſlaves of the devil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a proportion without proportion, &amp; (to ſpeak like a Geometrician) a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between a body and the ſhorteſt line.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>From <hi>Moſes</hi> let us paſs to that Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> by whoſe authority
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62319:66"/> we ſhall learn that this moſt bleſſed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is perſpicuouſly exaggerated. He pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth words of great conſolation upon the Church, even then Militant, <hi>Rejoyce O barren, thou that didſt not bear, break forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinging and cry aloud, thou that didſt not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with child. For more are the children of the deſolate, than the married wif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Which words are both cited and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians, Many more,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are the children of the deſolate, than of her that hath an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> Now they that are experienced in knowledge of Divine myſteries, are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that the Church of God is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by that deſolate and barren, and the kingdom of Satan by the married wife, for in the ſame place the Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth them one from the other, by moſt certain notes. <hi>Now we brethren,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Promiſe, as Iſaac was: but as then, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo it is now. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vertheleſs, caſt out the bond-woman and her ſon, for the ſon of the bond-woman ſhall not be Heir with the ſon of the free-woman.</hi> Therefore we are not, my brethren, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the bond-woman, but of the free.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I have heard, and as I remember I have read, that that barren was the Church collected out of all nations, &amp; that the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wife was the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:62319:66"/> the Synagogue of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which differ nothing but in Nation and time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it, and therefore I alleadged this place of the Apoſtle, that it might plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that they are not diſtinguiſhed by reaſon of Nation and time, but for inward qualifications, for manners, for conditions, and for the end. For firſt he diſtributes all mankind into thoſe that are born of the fleſh, and thoſe that are born of the Spirit, beſides theſe two, there is no third. Then he ſaith, <hi>Thoſe that are worldly, do continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vex and perſecute thoſe that are Spiritual and Heavenly, yet they are ſervants, theſe are free.</hi> Therefore in reference to their final condition, he conferreth an everlaſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance upon the ſons of the free-woman, thoſe of the bondwoman being abdicated, forſaken, and rejected. Theſe things being ſo learnedly and ſo plainly disjoyned by the Apoſtle, we ought not to conjoyn, or rather to confound them. And if any man will by that <hi>married wife,</hi> or by that <hi>daughter</hi> of the <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd-woman,</hi> underſtand the Nation of the <hi>Jews:</hi> neither can he by that means detract from the multitude of the Elect: for as he that treads the ſteps of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> is the ſon of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and belongeth to the number of the Saints; ſo he that followeth the contumacy, and abideth in the unbelief of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is deſervedly called a <hi>Hagaren,</hi> and an <hi>Iſmaelite.</hi> Here is therefore no place
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62319:67"/> for tergiverlation; for he plainly affirmeth that the number of the Citizens of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is much greater than that of the earthly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and this is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that great admiration of the celeſtial Citizens, when they behold their own mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as you read at large in the Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo; but why is one called barren, and forſaken; &amp; the other the married wife?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe ſhe is not ſo fruitful, pompous, and illuſtrious in the ceremonies of the Law as the other: Secondly, becauſe ſhe appeareth little and regardleſs in the eyes of the world. For ſhe boaſteth not of good works and merit: doth not make orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, magnificence, and ſplendour, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperable notes of her purity; and Laſtly, is not celebrated for diverſity of Sects, and variety of rites and ceremonies. Therefore ſhe is termed barren, without children, ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, little, deſpiſable, and forſaken of God, by them that judge according to the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious outſide of things. But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the other ſaid to have a husband, becauſe ſhe ſurpaſſeth in the pomp of outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for the Prophet hath oppoſed the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried woman to the barren, and her that is forſaken: and ſpeaks of both of them after the manner of men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not here demand who is the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the Church, for I know it is Chriſt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62319:67"/> the Lord: but who beſides will they have to be her huſband?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The very Synagogue it ſelf boaſts of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but very falſly, as Chriſt ſheweth in the 5. of <hi>John,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Had ye believed</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>ye had alſo believed me, for he wrote of me: but if ye believe not his writings, how will you believe my words?</hi> Alſo our Lord ſaith in the 2. of the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> that <hi>ſuch are not Jews, but blaſphemers, and the Synagogue of Satan.</hi> Moreover they who ordain and pretend <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> for their Law-giver, if they ſeek ſalvation by any other Law than that of Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or Pope, or any Seperatiſt whatſoever, they may be ſaid to have a maſter &amp; a husband, and they that are ſuch, are all ſervants &amp; bond-men, and as many as are begotten of them, that is, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by them: and if they be ſervants, they ſhall not abide in the houſe for ever, but the ſon abideth ever. But Chriſt and his Spouſe, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, have children, and thoſe free from the Law, as our Saviour told the <hi>Jews, If the Son ſhall make you free, then you are free;</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo telleth us, that <hi>where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. Therefore theſe are heirs, not by the obſervation of the Law, but only as ſons, ſons of the free-woman, which is the Holy Catholick Church, not the ſynagogue of the bond-woman, held under fear and ſervitude. For he that is a ſon, doth not imagine that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62319:68"/> he ſhall therefore become an heir, becauſe he ſerves the father &amp; keeps his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but becauſe he is born in true and lawful wedlock, or elſe called into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily by adoption.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things are ſo plain, that he is wilfully blind that ſeeth them not. But can you produce any teſtimonies out of the New Teſtament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I can; Behold S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> comparing the calamity brought into the world by the tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam,</hi> with the benefit of Chriſts reſurrection, that is, thoſe which were damned in <hi>Adam,</hi> with thoſe that are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſanctified and ſaved in Chriſt, ſaith thus, <hi>But not as the offence, ſo is the free gift, for if through the offence of one, many be dead: much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man Jeſus Chriſt, hath abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto many,</hi> Rom. 5. Now the ſenſe of the words is this, That the gift of one man Jeſus Chriſt, hath abounded to many more, than the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the offence by that fall did extend. Here you ſee the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>in terminis,</hi> that more are ſaved by the advantage of Chriſt, than are damned by the ſin of <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I do ſee it, and I underſtand it; but how in the ſame place are thoſe words to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood? For he ſaith, <hi>As by the offence of one man, judgement came upon all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; ſo by the righteouſneſs of one man,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62319:68"/> ſhall all men be abſolved.</hi> Here he ſaith all men are damned, and yet all men are ſaved, and ſeems to ſpeak things repugnant. For if all be condemned, there is a neceſſity none can be ſaved; and there is a neceſſity none can be damned, if all men be ſaved.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>You have propounded a queſtion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perplexed and knotty, but by Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance I ſhall untie it: I know there are ſome that ſay, all are condemned, that is, all that are born under original ſin, are obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious to condemnation: that all are abſolved and ſet free, that is, that Chriſt died for all men, and that his death was effectual to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation of the ſins of the whole world, if all men had applied unto themſelves the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his death by ſaith; but this opinion tottereth, in regard that all men are born in original ſin; yet all men are not juſtified, all men are not ſaved: and by this it would ſeem that the efficacy of the paſſion of Chriſt was not ſo diffuſive, as the tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam</hi> was deſtructive, whereas if you conſider the words onely, the reaſon ſhould be the ſame in both. You have not forgotten the old Axiomes, <hi>Paria paribus, &amp; contrariis omnibus contraria conveniunt.</hi> But this ſeems more plain to me to affirm, that all which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, are condemned for the offence of one man; and ſo alſo all that are ſaved, have ſalvation by the benefit of one; but it is true that all are condemned that came of the old
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62319:69"/> 
                     <hi>Adam,</hi> and all which are born of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> which is Chriſt, are ſaved; but they are <hi>few,</hi> theſe are <hi>many,</hi> otherwiſe the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt, will be found leſs than the <hi>diſobedience</hi> of <hi>Adam.</hi> Thus we ſhall with the Apoſtle, harbour thoughts correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Office &amp; Divine virtue of Chriſt. And whereas it follows, that by the <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nce</hi> of one, many were made ſubject to the curſe, we have already ſhewed that by <hi>many,</hi> the Apoſtle means <hi>all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I remember it, and like very well of your interpretation; but go on, becauſe I ſee you are ready to make an end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>To the amplitude of this Divine King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, thoſe places alſo do concur in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where the Father ſaith to his Son, <hi>Ask of me, and I ſhall give thee the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi> And in the 72. <hi>Pſalm, He ſhall have dominion alſo from ſea to ſea, and from the River unto the ends of the earth:</hi> alſo, <hi>All Kings ſhall worſhip him, and all Nations ſhall do him ſervice.</hi> Theſe paſſages of Scripture in the Hiſtory, belong to <hi>Solomon,</hi> but in the myſtery, to Chriſt our King, as thoſe that are converſant in the Scriptures, do well underſtand. Alſo that place in <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>I will pour forth of my Spirit upon all fleſh.</hi> Again in the 2. of the <hi>Acts, All men ſhall know me, even from the leaſt to the greateſt:</hi> Alſo in the firſt of <hi>Malac. From
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62319:69"/> the riſing of the Sun, even until the going down of the ſame, my Name ſhall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place incenſe ſhall be offered unto my Name, even a pure offering.</hi> Conſult alſo the Prophet, and obſerve in the ſeventh chapter, how honourable mention he maketh of the Kingdom of God. <hi>And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, ſhould ſerve him.</hi> Again in the 12. of <hi>John,</hi> our Lord ſaith of himſelf, <hi>And I, if I be lifted up, will draw all men unto me.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>That he doth enlighten all men,</hi> chap. 1. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo affirmeth, that <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved.</hi> And in another place, <hi>He hath ſhut up all men under unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all men.</hi> In theſe and very many other places, by the word <hi>all,</hi> is intimated the amplitude of the Kingdom of God. This is that ſeed, that fruitful off-ſpring, which <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> fore-ſeeing, was forced with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cry out, <hi>Who can declare his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> This is that multitude declared by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7. <hi>After this I beheld, and to a great multitude which no man could number, of all Nations, and Kindreds, and People, and Tongues, ſtood before the Throne, and before the Lamb, cloathed with white robes, and palms in their hands: and cryed out with a loud voyce, Salvation unto God, which ſitteth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb.</hi> This multitude, this
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62319:70"/> majeſty and greatneſs of the Kingdom of God, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture generations will better comprehend than the ages paſt; for they ſhall behold the moſt happy ſpreading of the Goſpel, they ſhall ſee the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Prince of the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> and of that proud Vicar of hell. Antichriſt by little and little ſhall be overcome, and caſt into utter darkeneſs, from whence there is no redemption: and they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo who have followed his voice, and obeyed his imaginations, ſhal participate the ſame damnation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh how happy hath this day been unto me, wherein I have learned the explanation of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficult places of Scripture, ſo great errours detected and confuted, ſo many miſteries revealed, and ſo many knotty and involved queſtions unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled. The cloud of errour being blown over, I now plainly ſee, how raſh and bold an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe it is, to judge of the Kingdom of Heaven by appearances, which is not conſtituted by any thing ſubjected to our ſenſes, but prepared by the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, and diſtinguiſhed from the ſynagogue of the devil, by faith and the fruits of the Holy Spirit, not purchaſed by any counſel, help, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ours, but obtained meerly by the gratious good pleaſure of our God. Wherefore from hence, forth I will forbear all ſuch temerity, and will leave the diſpoſing of his Kingdom, and the regle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his affairs, to God himſelf, who enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it at ſeveral times, and in ſeveral places, as beſt ſeemeth good unto him. I will know it to be my duty, to worſhip God in Spirit, perpetually to exalt his mercy, to love and follow Chriſt, and to help all men, even mine enemies, with my care, my counſel, and all my beſt aſſiſtances.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>Hic murus aheneus eſto.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62319:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
